FX平方  DX
Mod f-x-square, d-x.
下次上課前請做完
So please finish Percival for next time.
我知道你們中很多人大學時都學過
I know many of you had this as undergraduates,
但複習一下也無妨
but it won't hurt to brush up.
謝謝  史蒂芬
Thank you, Steven.
走廊黑板上有高級傅立葉算式
I also put an advanced Fourier system on the main hallway chalkboard.
希望學期結束前有人會解
I'm hoping that one of you might prove it by the end of the semester.
解出來的人不只有好成績...
Now the person to do so will not only be in my good graces...
還可因此紀錄名利雙收...
but also go on to fame and fortune...
他的成績記錄和大名...
by having their accomplishment recorded and their name printed...
將流傳于麻省理工學院
in the auspicious M.I.T. Tech.
之前解答包括諾貝爾獎得主  菲爾茲獎得主...
Former winners include Nobel laureates, Field's medal winners...
天文物理學家  還有卑賤的麻省理工教授
renowned astrophysicists and lowly M.I.T. professors.
就這樣  如果有問題...
Well, that's all. If you have any questions...
我相信湯姆會解答
I'm sure that Tom has the answers.
威爾
Hi, Will.
-克裡斯汀  你好嗎  -很好  你呢
-Kirsten, how you doing? -I'm all right. How are you?
-好  -我昨晚沒上凱西
-Good. -I didn't get on Cathy last night.
-沒有  -沒有
-No? -No.
-為什麼  -不知道
-Why not? -I don't know.
-凱西  -幹嘛
-Cathy! -What?
為什麼不像平時那樣...
Why didn't you give me none of that nasty little hoochie-woochie...
-讓我爽歪歪  -去你的...
-you usually throw at me? -Oh, fuck you...
還有你的愛爾蘭髒話
and your Irish curse, Chuckie.
我才不要吃飽飯為了你的小老二張開腿
Like I'd waste my energy spreading my legs for that Tootsie Roll dick?
-回家自己打手槍去吧  -小老二
-Go home and give it a tug yourself. -Tootsie Roll!
小老二
T-Toots!
她少一顆牙  威爾
She's missing a tooth, Will.
她皮膚也有問題  我...
She's got skin problems. I don't...
況且到頭來摩根八成會娶她  你知道我什麼意思
Plus, it's like 5-to-2 Morgan ends up marrying her, you know what I mean?
朋友的准老婆只能上幾次
There's only so many times you can bang your friend's future wife.
錯了  你去哪
It's wrong. Where you going?
-我要走了  -我操  才十點就要走
-I'm gonna take off. -Fuck you, you're taking off. It's, like, what, 10:00?
我累了
No, I'm tired.
愛爾蘭髒話
Irish curse?
她懂什麼  根本沒有愛爾蘭髒話
She don't know. There are'nt no Irish curse.
別老故意打到我
Out! Stop pressuring me back.
不要再靠近本壘板  是哪一樣
Stop crowding the plate! Which one will it be?
你會被起訴  你知道嗎
You're gonna get charged, you know that?
你以為我怕你啊  是你他媽的太靠近本壘板
You think I'm afraid of you, you big fuck? You're crowding the fucking plate.
蓋西下禮拜會在哈佛的酒吧
Hey, uh, Casey's bouncing up a bar at Harvard next week.
我們應該去
We should go up there.
-到那邊幹嘛  -不知道
-What are we gonna do up there? -I don't know.
去整聰明小孩  你很擅長
We'll fuck up some smart kids. Probably fit right in.
臭痞子
Ow! Fucking punk.
-怎樣  你很凶嗎  -來啊
-Oh, what's up? You still tough? -Come on!
來啊  對  約翰  來啊
Come on. Come on. That's it.
麻省理工學院校友會
-藍勃教授  -有何貴幹
-Professor Lambeau? -Yes?
我是你的應用理論課學生
I'm in your applied theories class.
我們都是數學和科技學院的
We're all up at the math and science building.
過來  今天禮拜六
Come here. It's Saturday.
-除非你今晚陪我喝酒  -或許吧
-Unless you wanna have a drink with me tonight. -Maybe.
但我們急著想弄清楚
We just couldn't wait until Monday to find out.
-弄清楚什麼  -是誰解出傅立葉算式
-Find out what? -Who proved the theorem.
完全正確  誰解的
This is correct. Who did this?
-傑克  -不是我
-Jack? -It wasn't me.
-尼米許  -不可能
-Nemesh? -N-No way.
快點  喬依  快跑
Come on, Joey, now!
比利  麥克馬拉要上了
Billy, McNamara's up.
放馬過來  小子
Come on, kid!
-喬依  拿下  拿下  -雜種
-Joey, dig it out! Dig it out! -Son of a bitch!
快放下  麥克  這樣才對
Bring it down, Mac! That's how to do it!
做得好  二壘  往二壘跑
Attaboy! Take two, Mac.
摩根  穿條紋褲的俏屁股女人是誰  那屁股真不賴
Hey, Morgan, who's the girl with the striped pants? She's got a nice ass.
-嗯  屁股不賴  -她跟誰一起
-Yeah, that's a real nice ass. -Who's the guy she's with?
是他媽的卡邁  我討厭他  威爾認識他
That fucking guinea. I hate that little bitch. Will knows him.
是的  他媽的卡邁
Yeah, I do. Yeah, fucking Carmine Scarpaglia.
-他幼稚園時把我揍得好慘  -那個人
-That guy used to beat the shit out of me in kindergarten. -That guy?
嗯
Yeah. Mm-hmm.
操他媽的  去弄點東西吃吧
Fuck this. Let's get some food.
-摩根  你不跟她講話嗎  -去她的
-Oh, what, Morgan, you're not gonna go talk to her? -Fuck her.
-我寧可吃大漢堡  -到"凱利"去吧
-I could go for a Whopper. -Let's go to Kelly's.
我才不要去  你只是喜歡那兒的外賣女孩
Morgan, I'm not going to Kelly's just because you like the take-out girl.
而且要多繞15分鐘路
It's 15 minutes out of our way.
那他媽的有什麼事可以做  挪不出15分鐘嗎
What the fuck are we gonna do? We can't spare 15 minutes?
大漢堡
Double burger.
查克  我有點大漢堡
Chuck, I had a double burger.
閉嘴  我知道你點什麼
Would you shut the fuck up! I know what you ordered. I was there.
那就把我的三明治給我
So give me my fucking sandwich.
什麼叫你的三明治  是我買的
What do you mean, your sandwich? I bought it.
摩根  你身上有多少錢
Morgan, how much money you got on you?
買霜淇淋就會有零錢了嘛
I said I'd get change when I get the snow cone.
停車後  把漢堡給我  別這麼討厭
I said that when we pulled up. Give me my sandwich and stop being a prick.
好  把身上的一毛六給我
All right, well, give me your fucking 16 cents that you got on you now.
我讓你他媽的分期付款買漢堡
We'll put your fucking sandwich on layaway.
漢堡擺這邊
Here we go. Keep it right up here for ya.
讓你分期付款  每天六分錢
We'll put you on a program. Every day you come in here with your six cents.
-週末給你漢堡  -你怎麼這麼惡劣
-At the end of the week, you get your sandwich. -Are you gonna be an asshole?
你他媽的以為我賣慈濟漢堡啊
What am I, fucking sandwich welfare?
你應該建立良好信用
I think you should establish a good line of credit.
對  就像你們買沙發那樣...分期付款
Like how you bought your couch... payment plans.
記得你媽每天存十塊錢嗎
Remember how your mother brought in ten dollars every day for a year.
最後她終於買到沙發了
She finally got her couch Rent-A-Center style.
-可以把食物給我了嗎  -把你的大漢堡拿去
-Can I have my food, please? -Here's your fucking double burger.
-哇  -等等  查克
-Whoa! -Hey, hold up, Chuck.
-慢下來  -怎麼了
-Slow it down. -Who do we got?
-還不知道  -傻帽
-I don't know yet. -Hey, douche bag!
你  你個混蛋
Yeah, you, you skank face!
-他媽的閉嘴  -下去  -你擔心什麼
-Shut the fuck up. -Get outta here. -What are you worried about?
你要舔舔我的小雞巴嗎
Why don't you lick my love stick?
15分鐘前才在公園看到他
We seen the guy 15 minutes ago.
當時就該扁他了  現在是吃零食的時間
We should've fight him then. We're eating our snacks now.
閉嘴  摩根  你也下去
Shut up, Morgan, you're going.
-我才不去  -那就別去
-I'm not going. -So don't go.
-我不去  -你他媽的給我去  摩根
-I'm not going. -Fucking go, Morgan.
我跟你講  兩秒內不滾出去
Let me tell you something. If you're not out there in two fucking seconds,
等我扁完他們  就扁你
when I'm done with them, you're next.
卡邁  是我  威爾  記得嗎
Carmine, it's me, Will. Remember,
我們是幼稚園同學
we went to kindergarten together.
-媽的  快走  兄弟  -踩爛他的臉
-Fucking, let's go, man. -Step on his fucking head.
讓他屁股著地  叫那傢伙住手  混蛋
Get his ass on the ground. Stop that motherfucker.
混蛋  去死吧
Motherfucker, die!
-卡特  -快走
-Carter! -Come on!
威爾  威爾  快走
Will! Will, come on!
威爾  條子  快走  快走
Will, come on. Let's go. Let's go.
別激動  別激動
Easy, brother, easy.
-謝謝你們出來  -過來
-Hey, fellas, thanks for coming out. -Come here!
哇  哇
Whoa! Whoa!
操
Ah. Fuck.
我這是做夢  還是班級變大了
Is it just my imagination, or has my class grown considerably?
不出意料的話...
Well, by no stretch of my imagination...
你們是來聽我講課
do I believe you've all come here to hear me lecture.
或想知道神秘數學奇才是誰
Rather, to ascertain the identity of the mystery math magician.
別再不告而別  沉默的天才  出來領獎吧
So without further adieu, come forward, silent rogue, and receive thy prize.
抱歉讓觀眾失望了  但是...
Well, I'm sorry to disappoint my spectators, but...
看來今天不會揭曉了
it seems there will be no unmasking here today.
我和同事決定再下戰帖
However, uh, my colleagues and l have conferred,
外面黑板上有個題目...
and there is a problem on the board right now...
我們花了兩年時間才解開
that took us more than two years to prove.
請沉默的天才再解解看
So let this be said: The gauntlet has been thrown down,
全體教授已備有解答
but the faculty have answered and answered with vigor.
幾時提訊
Hey, when's the arraignment?
下星期
Next week.
對不起
Sorry.
-你在做什麼  -對不起
-What are you doing? -Sorry.
那是別人的勞動  你不能在人家的方程式上塗鴉
That's people's work. You can't graffiti here.
-你別走  -去你的
-Don't you walk away from me! -Hey, fuck you!
別耍聰明  你叫什麼名字
Oh, you're a clever one. What's your name?
我的天
Oh, my God.
好像是對的
Looks right.
要多智障才會被開除
Will, how retarded do you gotta be to get fired from that job?
我是說  在屋子裡掃地有那麼難嗎
I mean, how hard is it to push a motherfucking broom around?
麥琪  你連掃地都會被開除
Mitch, you got fired from pushing a fucking broom.
那是因為管理階層重組
I got fired because management was restructuring.
對  重組智障兒的數量
Yeah, restructuring the amount of retards they had working for them.
閉嘴  你被開除的次數更多
Shut up. You get canned more than tuna, bitch.
起碼現在我有工作  不是嗎
At least I got a motherfucking job right now, don't I?
-威爾  你為何被開除  快說  -管理階級重組
-Why'd you get fired, Will? Come on. -Management was restructuring.
-我舅舅或許能給你工作  -他可以幫我嗎
-My uncle could probably get you on a demo team. -Can he do that?
你耍我  我昨天還問過你
You kidding me! I asked you yesterday if I could get a job.
我昨天告訴你"不行"
And I told you "no" yesterday.
怎麼樣  蓋斯
What's up, Casey?
-怎麼樣  蓋斯  -怎麼樣  蓋斯
-What's up, Case? -What's up, Big Case?
坐這邊
Let's sit over here.
好的  走吧
All right. Let's go.
這就是...這就是哈佛酒吧
Oh, this is... this is a Harvard bar, huh?
我以為牆上會有方程式呢
I thought there'd be, like, equations and shit on the wall.
我要一壺店裡最好的啤酒
I will take a pitcher of the finest lager in the house.
暫停  我要去泡
Timeout. I'm gonna have to bust a little move on
吧台的哈佛辣妹
them Harvard hotties down there at the bar.
-幹得漂亮點  -幫我們也釣幾個
-Work some magic. -Get some potion for us.
-哈羅  -哈羅
-Oh, hello. -Oh, hello.
-你好嗎  -好
-Hi. How are ya? -Fine.
-那麼  兩位美女...-常來嗎
-So, do you ladies, uh... -Come here often?
我常來嗎  我很少到這裡
Do I come here? I come here a bit.
你知道  我只是偶爾來
I'm here, you know, from time to time.
-你們在這兒念書  -對
-Do you go to school here? -Yep.
就是嘛  我想我跟你同班
Yeah, that's it. I think I had a class with you.
是嗎  哪一班
Oh, yeah. What class?
-歷史  -或許
-History. -Maybe.
應該沒錯
Yes, I think that's what it was.
你可能...不記得我  你知道  我喜歡這裡
You don't necessarily... may not remember me. You know, I like it here.
我來這邊並不表示我是天才  但我還是很聰明
It doesn't mean because I go here, I'm a genius. I am very smart.
嘿
Hey.
-過的怎樣  你好嗎  -好  你呢
-Hey, how's it going? How are ya? -Good. How ya doing?
你說你在哪一班
What class did you say that was?
-歷史  -對
-History. -Yeah.
單單歷史  那一定是概論課程
Just history? It must have been a survey course then.
-對  是概論課程  -好的
-Yeah, it was. It was surveys. -Right.
你應該上上看  不錯的課程  不錯的班級
You should check it out. It's a good course. It'd be a good class.
-你覺得那堂課怎麼樣  -老實說
-How'd you like that course? -You know, frankly,
-我覺得相當基礎  -基礎
-I found that class, you know, rather elementary. -Elementary.
-肯定是的  -嗯
-You know, I don't doubt that it was. -Yeah.
我記得那堂課了
I, uh, I remember that class.
就...就在休息和午餐之間
It was, um... It was just between recess and lunch.
克拉克  你走開啦
Clark, why don't you go away?
-放輕鬆點  -走開啦
-Why don't you relax? -Why don't you go away?
-我跟我的新朋友很開心  -有什麼問題嗎
-I'm just having fun with my new friend. -Are we gonna have a problem?
不  不  不  沒問題
No, no, no, no. There's no problem here.
只是想請教你對於市場經濟...
I was just hoping you might give me some insight into the evolution...
在南部殖民地發展的看法
of the market economy in the southern colonies.
我主張在革命戰爭前...
My contention is that prior to the Revolutionary War, the economic modalities...
南方殖民地的經濟形態...
especially in the southern colonies...
最適合被刻畫為...
could most aptly be characterized as...
-農地  -讓我跟你說兩句
-agrarian precapitalist. -Let me tell you something.
那當然是你的論點  新生嘛
Of course that's your contention. You're a first-year grad student.
才剛念完馬克思主義...
You just got finished reading some Marxian historian...
也許念到皮特·蓋瑞森...
Pete Garrison, probably...
下個月念到雷蒙的論點  你會更深信不疑
You're gonna be convinced of that till next month when you get to James Lemon.
然後你會談到
Then you're gonna be talking about
維吉尼亞州及賓夕法尼亞州...
how the economies of Virginia and Pennsylvania...
在1740年如何企業化與資本主義化
were entrepreneurial and capitalist way back in 1740.
一直持續到
That's gonna last until next year.
明年你反芻伍德
You're gonna be in here regurgitating Gordon Wood,
大談革命前烏托邦...
talking about, you know, the prerevolutionary utopia...
和軍事動員對資本形成的影響
and the capital-forming effects of military mobilization.
事實上我反對這個觀點
Well, as a matter of fact, I won't,
因為伍德完全低估了...
because Wood drastically underestimates the impact of...
伍德低估了社會財富的差異...
Wood drastically underestimates the impact of social distinctions...
尤其是繼承財富
predicated upon wealth, especially inherited wealth.
這是你從維克斯讀到的論點
You got that from Vickers' Work in
"艾群就業分析"  98頁  對嗎
Essex County. Page 98, right?
我也讀過  你要剽竊整本書嗎
I read that too. Were you gonna plagiarize the whole thing for us?
對這些論點你有個人想法嗎
Do you have any thoughts of your own on this matter?
你動過腦子嗎  你跑到酒吧來  高談書中的論點
Or is that your thing? You come into a bar. You read some obscure passage.
還假裝...是自己的觀點
Then pretend... pawn it off as your own.
就為了泡妞  糗我朋友嗎
As your own idea just to impress some girls? Embarrass my friend?
可悲的是在五十年後
See, the sad thing about a guy like you is, in 50 years,
你才會開始瞭解
you're gonna start doing some thinking on your own.
生命中有兩件事是確定的
You're gonna come up with the fact that there are two certainties in life.
一  是別只會打高空
One: Don't do that.
二  你花一萬五所受的教育...
And two: You dropped 150 grand on a fucking education...
用一塊五就能在圖書館得到
you could've got for $1.50 in late charges at the public library.
對  但我會有文憑
Yeah, but I will have a degree,
你卻只能在我去滑雪勝地途中
and you'll be serving my kids fries at a drive through
賣薯條給我的小孩
on our way to a skiing trip.
或許吧  起碼我不會沒創意
Maybe, but at least I won't be unoriginal.
不爽的話可以到外面解決
If you have a problem with that, we could step outside. We could figure it out.
不  沒事  很酷
No, man, there's no problem. It's cool.
-酷  -對
-It's cool? -Yeah.
-對  -你他媽的酷斃了
-Cool. -Damn right, it's cool.
現在喜歡我了吧
How do you like me now?
那小子聰明絕頂
My boy's wicked smart.
才來三分鐘就擺平一個傻蛋  嗯哼
I just spent three minutes in this fucking place and run into a barney, huh?
有了
There it is.
-你好  -他們不錯
-Nice to meet you. -They were fine, man.
我們差點就要把到她們  結果比利...
I was gonna close the deal, but then Chuck...
觸怒到她們當中一人...
Billy insulted one of them...
辣妹就說我頭快禿了
The heavyset girl said I had a receding hairline,
人又太胖
and I was a few pounds overweight.
我就說"去你媽的"
And I was, like, "Go fuck yourself."
我什麼都沒說
I swallowed a bug.
嗨
Hi.
-你是個白癡  -什麼
-You're an idiot. -What?
你是個白癡  我坐在那邊45分鐘...
You're an idiot. I've been sitting over there for 45 minutes...
等你過來跟我講話
waiting for you to come and talk to me.
但我累了  我得回家了
But I'm tired now, and I have to go home.
我不能再坐著等你
I couldn't sit there anymore waiting for you.
-我是威爾  -史凱蘭
-I'm Will. -Skylar.
-史凱蘭  -對了
-Skylar. -Oh, and by the way,
那個人...邁可波頓二號...
that guy over there... Michael Bolton clone...
跟我們不是一國的
He wasn't sitting with us, so to speak.
-我知道  我看得出來  -好的
-I know. I kinda got that impression. -Good. Okay.
我得走了
Well, I've got to go.
我要早起花錢買文憑
Gotta get up early and waste some more money on my overpriced education.
-我不是指你  -沒關係
-No, I didn't mean you. -That's all right.
這是我的電話  也許有空可以喝杯咖啡
There's my number. Maybe we can go out for coffee sometime.
好  或許聚在一起吃焦糖
All right, yeah. Maybe we can just get together and eat a bunch of caramels.
-什麼意思  -想想看
-What do you mean? -When you think about it,
-那和喝咖啡一樣愜意  -是嗎  好吧
-it's as arbitrary as drinking coffee. -Oh. Yeah. Okay.
那好
Uh, right, then.
得了  你在開玩笑
Oh, come on. You're kidding.
喲
Yo!
-去你的  -我才去你的
-Fuck you, bitch! -Fuck you.
-那些傻屌在那邊  -等等
-There goes them fucking barneys right now with his skiing trip. -Hold on.
我們應該扁那個混蛋
We should've beat that old bitch's ass.
你喜歡青蘋果甜甜圈嗎
Do you like apples?
-喜歡  -喜歡
-Yeah. -Yeah?
我得到她的電話了  你卻只能吃甜甜圈
Well, I got her number! How do you like them apples?
打擾了  這是大樓管理室嗎
Excuse me? Is this the Buildings and Grounds office?
是的  有何貴幹
Yeah. What can I do for you?
我要找個在這裡打工的學生
I just need the name of a student who works here.
-沒學生替我做事  -請你查一下好嗎
-No students work for me. -Could you please check?
有個人在我那棟樓做事
I have this guy who works in my building.
-個子大概這麼高  -你是哪棟樓
-He's about this high. -Which one is your building?
-二棟  -二棟
-Two. -Two. Building two.
如果有東西失竊  我該知道
Look, if anything was stolen, I should know about it.
不是那樣
No, it's nothing like that.
我只是要找他
I just need his name.
除非你投訴  否則不能告訴你
I can't give you his name unless you have a complaint.
這位是藍勃教授
This is Professor Lambeau.
這位是海斯教授
And this is Professor Hayes.
湯姆  拜託
Tom, please.
這很重要
This is important. Please.
他今天沒上班
Will didn't show for work today.
他透過PO找到這份工作  你可以找到他
Got this job through his P.O. You can call him.
-PO  -對  觀護人
-P.O.? -Yeah. Parole officer.
謝謝
Thank you.
混蛋
Asshole.
法官先生  這溯及1789年的司法判例
There is a lengthy legal precedent, Your Honor, going back to 1789,
被告可對政府單位
whereby a defendant can claim self-defense against
要求自衛權...
an agent of the government...
如果該舉動是為保護自由  抗拒暴政制裁的話
if that act is deemed a defense against tyranny, a defense of liberty.
法官先生  1887年比徹爾
Your Honor, Henry Ward Beecher,
-曾在普利茅斯講道壇引述過...-1887
-in Proverbs from the Plymouth Pulpit, 1887, said, quote... -1887?
-怎麼了  -現在都20世紀了
-Excuse me. -This is the 20th century.
他在嘲弄法庭
He's gonna make a mockery.
憲法賦與我
I am afforded the right to speak in my own defense, sir,
為自己辯護之權
by the Constitution of the United States.
-別跟我扯憲法  -憲法保障了我的自由
-Don't tell me about the Constitution. -This guarantees my liberty.
"自由"  也許你淡忘了  是一個人呼吸的權利
"Liberty," in case you've forgotten, is a soul's right to breathe.
無法讓人呼吸的法律太嚴肅
When it cannot take a long breath, laws are girded too tight.
-不自由  人就是"行屍走肉"  -什麼
-Without liberty, man is a syncope. -Man is a what?
-出處同前  法官先生  -輪到我了
-Ibid., Your Honor. -Son, my turn.
我在這坐了十分鐘看著你的罪狀
I've been sitting here for ten minutes now looking over this rap sheet of yours.
我不敢相信  93年6月襲擊罪
I just can't believe it. June '93, assault.
93年9月襲擊罪
September '93, assault.
94年2月偷車罪
Grand theft auto, February of '94.
你引述"馬與馬車的財產權"...
Where, apparently, you defended yourself and had the case thrown out by citing...
並以自我辯護讓此案駁回
"free property rights of horse and carriage" from 1798.
95年1月  扮成員警
Joke. January '95, impersonating an officer.
傷害  竊盜  拒捕  全部駁回
Mayhem, theft, resisting. All overturned.
我知道你住過幾個寄養家庭
I'm also aware that you've been through several foster homes.
因受虐而從其中三個搬出
The state removed you from three because of serious physical abuse.
別的法官是關心你  但你打員警  就得坐牢
You know, another judge might care, but you hit a cop. You're going in.
不准提出抗告  保釋金五萬
Motion to dismiss is denied. $50,000 bail.
謝謝
Thank you.
起立
Rise.
-喂  -史凱蘭
-Hello? -Uh, Skylar?
-嗯  -我是威爾
-Yep. -Hey, uh, it's Will.
-誰  -我是威爾
-Who? -It's Will.
你前兩天在酒吧碰到的幽默有形的帥哥
You know, the really funny, good-looking guy you met at the bar the other night.
我不記得有碰到這樣的人
I don't recall meeting anyone who matches
我想起來了
that description. I think I'd remember.
好吧  是那個醜陋無比又沒牙...
Oh, all right, you got me. It's the ugly, obnoxious, toothless loser...
還整夜纏著你不放的廢物
who got hammered and wouldn't leave you alone all night.
威爾  我記起來了
Oh, Will! I remember.
你好嗎  我還在想你會不會打來
How are you? I was wondering if you'd call me.
-我一直在想...-怎麼樣  寶貝
-Yeah, look, I was wondering... -Yo, what's up, baby?
-稍等  -你要怎樣  寶貝  想上我嗎
-Hold on one second. -What you doing? Want some of my ass?
赫芙  我記得在少年監獄見過你  你好嗎
Herve, I remember you from juvi. How you doing?
幹嘛
What you doing?
對不起
Oh, yeah, sorry about that.
我在想也許這禮拜可以聚一聚
I was wondering maybe we could get together sometime this week.
-坐在咖啡座  吃點焦糖  -聽起來很棒
-Sit out at a cafe. Maybe have some caramels. -Oh, that sounds wonderful.
-可以嗎  -可以  你在哪裡
-Yeah? -Yeah, sure. Where are you?
我站的地方有點糟
Uh, well, actually, this is just a shot in the dark,
你那兒總不會是看守所吧
but, uh, there's no chance that you're pre-law, is there?
-坐  -謝謝
-Have a seat. -Thank you.
很高興跟你講話
Nice talking to ya.
你他媽的想幹嘛
What the fuck do you want?
我是傑洛藍勃
I'm Gerald Lambeau.
你叫他滾蛋的那個教授
Professor you told to fuck himself.
你他媽找我幹嘛
Well, what the fuck do you want?
我跟法官談過
I've spoken to the judge,
他同意在我監護之下放你出去
and he's agreed to release you under my supervision.
-真的  -是的
-Really? -Yeah.
-但有兩個條件  -哪兩個
-Under two conditions. -What are those?
第一個條件  你每週要跟我碰面
First condition is that you meet with me every week.
-做什麼  -和你討論數學
-What for? -Go over the proof you're working on,
給你做些更高級的...
get into some more advanced...
組合數學
combinatorial mathematics,
有限數學
finite math.
好像很有趣
Sounds like a real hoot.
第二個條件...
And the second condition is that...
你要看心理醫生
that you see a therapist.
由我每週負責作評估報告
I'm responsible to submit reports on those meetings.
如果你不及格  照樣送你回來坐牢
If you fail to meet with any of those conditions, you will have to serve time.
好  數學我接受
All right. I'll do the math,
但我不看去他的心理醫生
but I'm not gonna meet with any fucking therapist.
這總比蹲牢房好  不是嗎
It's better than spending that time in jail, isn't it?
我看過你的書  你提到有個病人麥克的問題...
I read your book, and "Mike" was having the same problems...
事實上和證券營業員查克一樣
that "Chad," the stockbroker, was having.
完全正確  說得很准  很好
Absolutely right. Right on the button. Good for you, Will.
-非常棒  -謝謝
-Very nice. -Thank you.
威爾  有關壓力...我不是評頭論足
Will, the pressures... and I'm not judging them.
也不是武斷地貼你標籤
I'm not labeling them,
但它破壞了你的潛力
but they are destroying your potential.
別再惡作劇  耍蠢  吹擂
No more shenanigans. No more tomfoolery. No more ballyhoo.
你說得對  天哪  我知道
You're right. God, I know.
要擺脫不容易  來  多講點
You're not gonna get off that easily. Come on, Will. A bit more.
我有做過一些事  知道嗎
Well, I mean, I do do things, you know?
哪...哪種事
What... What kind of things?
我做過的  你知道  我躲避人群
I do things that, you know, I mean, I hide from people.
你躲避
You hide, do you?
不  我是說  我也去一些地方交朋友
No, no. I mean, I like... I go places. I interact.
-真的  哪種地方  -一些酒吧
-Really? What sort of places? -Just certain clubs.
再來  很好  哪種酒吧
More. That's nice. Yes. What sort of clubs?
像是"幻想"
Like, uh, like Fantasy.
"幻想"  還不錯的地方  再多講點
Fantasy. That's nice. A bit more.
一進去整個人就被音樂包圍
It's something like when you get in there, the music, like, owns you.
浩勢音樂  就像...砰  砰  砰
It's like that house music. It's like... Bom, bom, bom
砰-砰-砰  砰  砰  砰  砰
Bom-bom-bom Boom, boom, boom, boom
-你就會開始跳舞  -砰  砰  砰  是的
-You know, you start dancing. -Boom, boom, boom. Yeah.
只是...
It's just...
是的
Yes.
隱瞞你是同性戀很難嗎
Do you find it hard to hide the fact that you're gay?
你在說什麼  什麼
What are you talking about? What?
兄弟  兩秒前你準備撲向我
Look, buddy, two seconds ago, you were ready to give me a jump.
撲  你...
A jump? Are you...
很抱歉讓你失望了
I'm terribly sorry to disappoint you.
沒關係  我不在乎你從後面上
Hey, I don't have a problem with it. I don't care if you putt from the rough.
你在說...從...從後面上你
What are you... P... Putting from the rough?
你在講什麼
What on earth are you talking about?
困難的定理就像交響曲
A difficult theorem could be like a symphony.
性感無比
It's very erotic.
你找別人  我應付不來
You go somewhere else. I can't handle this.
-哇  -謝謝  亨利
-Wow. -Thank you, Henry.
-啊  亨利  -嗨  傑洛
-Ah, Henry. -Hi, Gerry.
知道嗎  我不能再做這種公眾服務
You know something? I can't do this pro bono work anymore.
-這...不值得  -怎麼了
-It's just not... It's not worth it. -What happened?
下周我要上電視
Well, I'm going on national television next week.
沒空告訴你
I mean, I haven't got time to tell you,
更別提這個胡言亂語的瘋子
much less talk to that raving looney in there.
他簡直冥頑不靈
An absolute lunatic, he is.
亨利
Henry.
好  你在你床上
Okay, you are in your bed, Will.
你幾歲了
Now, how old are you?
七歲
Seven.
你看到什麼
What do you see?
我房裡有東西
Something's in my room.
是什麼
What is it?
是個...是個人形  在我頭上盤旋
It's like a... It's a figure. It's hovering over me.
你在安全的地方  威爾
You are in a safe place, Will.
他在...他在摸我
It's t... It's touching me.
他摸你哪裡
Where is it touching you?
摸我那下麵
It's touching me down there,
我很緊張
and I'm nervous.
不必緊張  威爾
You don't have to be nervous, Will.
我們開始跳舞
We start dancing and dancing.
好美
It's just beautiful,
因為日落前...
because we can make...
我們可以瘋狂地做愛
a lot of love before the sun goes down.
煙火飛舞
Skyrockets in flight
午後歡樂
Afternoon delight
-嘿  嘿  嘿  煙火飛舞  -天啊
-Hey, hey, hey, afternoon delight  -Jesus.
午後歡樂  嗒  嗒  嗒  嗒
Skyrockets in flight Da-da-da-da
-抱歉  瑞克  -怎樣安排時間我自有打算
-I'm sorry, Rich. -I have better things to do with my time.
嘿  嘿  午後歡樂  來  我們跳舞
Hey, hey, afternoon delight  Come on! One dance!
你把我催眠了  知道嗎
You really hypnotized me, you know?
看在老天份上  威爾
For God's sake, Will.
幹嘛  他走了  你別怪在我頭上
What? Oh, come on. He left. You can't pin that on me.
-你得跟這些人合作  -凝視...
-I told you to cooperate with these people. -Look...
-我的眼睛  -出去  威爾
-into my eyes. -Get out, Will.
我不需要治療
I don't need therapy.
夠了  出去
That's enough. Get out!
-我早上打過電話給梅爾...-有用嗎
-I called Mel Weintraub this morning to see... -Oh, what's the use?
你想怎麼做
What do you want to do?
-有個人  -是誰
-Well, there's someone. -Who is he?
他過去是我的...我的大學室友
He used to be my, uh... my roommate in college.
邦克山社區大學
信任  在感情上很重要
Trust. Very important in a relationship.
在臨床上也很重要
It's also very important in a clinical situation.
為何信任對於突破患者心防...
Why is trust the most important thing...
是最重要的關鍵
in making a breakthrough with a client?
莫琳  別老張著嘴  聽課
Maureen, stop the oral fixation for a moment and join us.
-維尼  -嗯...
-Vinnie. -Um...
因為...
Because, uh...
信任就是...就是生命
Trust is, uh... Trust is life.
很深奧  謝謝你  維尼
Wow. That's very deep. Thank you, Vinnie.
下次抄你弟弟的筆記
Next time, get the notes from your brother.
若病患不信任你
If a patient doesn't feel safe enough trust you,
就不會坦誠相對
then they won't be honest with you.
治療對他們來說就毫無意義
Then there's really no point for them being in therapy.
我是說  如果她們不信任你
I mean, hey, if they don't trust you,
就不會跟你上床
you're never gonna get them to sleep with you.
那該是心理醫生的最終目的
That should be the goal of any good therapist.
趁脆弱時下手
Nail them while they're vulnerable.
我的座右銘
That's my motto.
很好  大家都醒了  歡迎回來
Oh, good, everyone's back. Welcome back, everybody.
-你好  尚恩  -嗨  傑洛
-Hello, Sean. -Hey, Gerry.
女士們先生們  我們很榮幸請來一位大人物
Um, ladies and gentlemen, we are in the presence of greatness.
傑洛藍勃教授  組合數學的菲爾茲獎得主
Professor Gerald Lambeau, Fields medal winner for combinatorial mathematics.
-哈羅  -誰知道什麼是菲爾茲獎
-Hello. -Anyone know what the Field's medal is?
了不起  數學界的諾貝爾獎
It's a really big deal. It's like the Nobel prize for math.
只是它四年才頒一次  很偉大
Except they only give it out once every four years. It's a great thing.
是驚人的榮耀  今天就到此為止  下課
It's an amazing honor. Okay, everybody, that's it for today.
謝謝  禮拜一見  下次我們談佛洛伊德
Thanks. We'll see you Monday. We'll be talking about Freud.
他為何用古柯鹼殺馬  謝謝
Why he did enough cocaine to kill a small horse. Thank you.
-你好嗎  -真高興見到你
-How are you? -It's good to see you.
很高興見到你
Good to see you.
-尚恩  我有一件你會感興趣的事  -是嗎
-Sean, I think I got something interesting for ya. -Yeah?
需要血液和尿液嗎  幹嘛
What, you have to have blood and urine? What's up?
同學會你怎麼不來
Why didn't you come to the reunion?
我...我在忙
You know, I'm... I've been busy.
-大家很想你  -真的
-You were missed. -Really?
-我們多久沒見面了  -南茜去世前
-So how long has it been since we've seen each other? -Before Nancy died.
是  很抱歉
Yeah, I'm sorry.
我在巴黎開會  都是那該死的會議
I was in Paris. It was that damn conference.
我收到你寄來的卡片  很好
I got your card. It was nice.
-過來  -投得不錯
-Come here. -Now that's a takedown.
怎麼樣  博得同情沒
Hey, what happened? Did you get leniency or what?
獲得保釋和一周兩次的輔導
I got, uh, probation and then counseling two days a week.
真不是蓋的  你伶牙利嘴
Joke. You're a smoothie.
快  摩根  快投球
Come on, Morgan! Just submit!
比爾  放開他  我們會錯過球賽的
Hey, Bill, just-just get off him. We're gonna miss the game.
-我行程很滿  我很忙  -尚恩  尚恩
-I've got a full schedule. I'm very busy. -Sean, Sean.
這孩子不可思議  前所未見
This-This boy is incredible. I've never seen anything like him.
是什麼讓他這麼不可思議
What makes him so incredible, Gerry?
-聽過拉瑪努強嗎  -聽過  沒有
-You ever heard of Ramanujan? -Yeah, yeah. No.
他是個男人  活在一百多年前  印度人
It's a man. He lived over 100 years ago. He was Indian.
-卓越成就  -卓越成就  嗯
-Dots, not feathers. -Not feathers. Yeah.
他住在茅屋裡
He lived in this tiny hut somewhere in India.
沒受過正規教育
He had no formal education.
-無法取得任何科學著述  -來杯咖啡
-He had no access to any scientific work. -Coffee?
-您呢  先生  -來一點點
-You, sir? -Just a little.
但他偶然發現一本舊數學課本
But he came across this old math book,
從簡單的條條框框  他推導出深奧的理論...
and from the simple text, he was able to extrapolate theories...
多年來難倒無數數學家
that had baffled mathematicians for years.
對  連續分數  他是以...
Yes. Continued fractions. He wrote, uh...
-他寄給劍橋的哈帝  -嗯  劍橋
-Well, he mailed it to Hardy at Cambridge. -Yeah, Cambridge. Yeah.
-哈帝即刻瞭解那是天才之作...-嗯
-And Hardy immediately recognized the brilliance of his work... -Mm-hmm.
把他帶到英國  然後他們合作多年
and brought him over to England, and then they worked together for years,
創造出令人興奮的數學理論
creating some of the most exciting math theory ever done.
拉瑪努強...
This-This Ramanujan...
他的天才無與倫比
his-his genius was unparalleled, Sean.
-這孩子就像他一樣  -嗯
-Well, this boy's just like that. -Hmm.
-但他...有點防禦性  -嗯
-But he's... he's a bit defensive. -Hmm.
我需要有人突破他的心防
I need someone who can get through to him.
-像是我  -對  就是你
-Like me? -Yeah, like you.
-為什麼  -因為你們有相同背景
-Why? -Well, because you have the same kind of background.
-什麼背景  -你們來自同一個區
-What background? -Well, you're from the same neighborhood.
-他是南區人  -是的
-He's from Southie? -Yeah.
南區的天才少年
Boy genius from Southie.
-你之前找過幾個心理醫生  -五個
-How many shrinks you go to before me? -Five.
-讓我猜  拜瑞  亨利  沒找瑞克吧  -是的
-Let me guess. Barry? Henry? Not Rick? -Yeah. Yeah.
-尚恩  請跟他碰面  一週一次就好  -嗯哼
-Sean, please, just meet with him once a week. -Mm-hmm.
拜託你
Please?
這就像打牌  別讓牌洩底
It's a poker game with this kid. Don't let him know what you've got.
要是他碰過你的書  那他或許就已經看過你的書
He probably even read your book, if he could find it.
他要找到很難
It's gonna be hard for him to find.
-嗨  威爾  -嗨
-Hi, Will. -Hi.
這是尚恩麥圭爾  威爾杭汀
This is Sean Maguire. Will Hunting.
你好
How are ya?
-來吧  開始治療吧  -好  開始吧
-Yeah. Let's get started. -Yeah, let's do it.
我迫不及待了  快開始療程
I'm pumped. Let's let the healing begin.
-請出去一下  -對  麻煩你  湯姆
-Will you excuse us? -Yeah, please, Tom.
你也出去  傑洛
You, too, Gerry.
好  當然
Yeah, of course.
你好嗎
How are you?
你是南區哪裡人
Where you from in Southie?
-我喜歡你這邊的裝潢  -謝謝
-I like what you've done with the place. -Oh, thanks.
這些書都是零買的
Do you buy all these books retail,
還是派人買的
or do you send away for, like, a "shrink kit"
整套心理叢書
that comes with all these volumes included?
-你喜歡看書  -喜歡
-Do you like books? -Yeah.
-這些書你讀過嗎  -不知道
-Did you read any of these books? -I don't know.
-那些書呢  -大概沒有
-How about any of these books? -Probably not.
頂層那些呢  看過沒
What about the ones on the top shelf? You read those?
-看過  -很好  你有什麼感想
-Yeah, I read those. -Good for you. What do you think about them?
我不是他媽的來做讀書報告
I'm not here for a fucking book report.
那是你的書  你怎麼不讀
They're your books. Why don't you read them?
我讀過  非讀不可
I did. I had to.
-一定花了你不少時間  -是的
-Must've taken you a long time. -Yeah, it did.
美國通史  第一冊
United States of America: A Complete History, Volume l.
天哪  若想看真的歷史
Jesus. If you wanna read a real history book,
你應該讀辛恩的書
read Howard Zinn's A People's History in the United States.
那本書會讓你大吃一驚
That book'll fucking knock you on your ass.
比喬姆斯基的書更好嗎
Better than Chomsky's Manufacturing Consent?
-你覺得那是本好書  -我搞不懂你們這些人
-Do you think that's a good book? -You fucking people baffle me.
把錢花在這種他媽的垃圾書上面
You spend all your money on these fucking fancy books.
還讀得津津有味
You surround yourselves with them.
-這些是漏洞百出的書  -什麼是漏洞百出的書
-They're the wrong fucking books. -What are the right fucking books, Will?
-讓你頭髮豎起來的  -嗯  我剩的頭髮不多
-Whatever blows your hair back. -Yeah. Haven't got much hair left.
要是你把煙戒了
Hey, you know you'd be better shoving that cigarette up your ass.
-可能會健康點  -我知道
-It'd probably be healthier for you. -Yeah, I know.
-抽煙妨礙我練瑜珈  -你運動嗎
-It really gets in the way of my yoga. -You work out, huh?
-你舉重嗎  -嗯
-What, you lift? -Yeah.
-舉重機  -不  啞鈴
-Nautilus? -No, free weights.
-真的  啞鈴  -你舉多少
-Oh, really? Free weights, huh? -Yeah. Yeah, big time.
-是嗎  -就是那樣
-Yeah? -Just like that.
-你舉多少  -285  你呢
-What do you bench? -285. What do you bench?
你畫的
You paint that?
-對  你畫畫嗎  -不
-Yeah. Do you paint? -Uh-uh.
-你雕塑嗎  -不
-Do you sculpt? -No.
喜歡藝術嗎
Do you like art?
-喜歡音樂嗎  -真爛
-Do you like music? -This is a real piece of shit.
告訴我你覺得怎麼樣
Oh, tell me what you really think.
線條結構複雜混亂
Just the linear and impressionistic mix makes a very muddled composition.
筆法頗有印象派畫風  除了有白人在划船
It's also a Winslow Homer rip-off, except you got whitey rowing the boat there.
那倒怪了  我並不想模仿莫內
Well, it's art, Monet. It wasn't very good.
-我在意的不是那個  -你在意什麼
-That's not really what concerns me though. -What concerns you?
-只是色彩  -你知道這幅畫的靈魂是什麼
-Just the coloring. -You know what the real bitch of it is?
這幅畫是以數字畫的
It's paint-by-number.
以數字上色  至少這色彩讓我著迷
Is it color-by-number? Because the colors are fascinating to me.
-真的  -我保證
-Aren't they really? -You bet.
我想你差點就要割耳朵了
I think you're about one step away from cutting your fucking ear off.
-真的  -沒錯
-Really? -Oh, yeah.
那我應該搬到法國改名為"梵古"
Think I should move to the south of France, change my name to "Vincent"?
-聽過"暴風雨中的港口"嗎  -聽過
-You ever heard the saying, "any port in a storm"? -Yeah.
-也許指的就是你  -哪方面
-Yeah, maybe that means you. -In what way?
也許你正在暴風雨中  劇烈的暴風雨中
Maybe you're in the middle of a storm, a big fucking storm.
可能吧
Yeah, maybe.
天色昏暗  海浪撞擊小船
The sky's falling on your head. The waves are crashing over your little boat.
槳就要斷了
The oars are about to snap.
你嚇壞了  迫切需要港口
You just piss in your pants. You're crying for the harbor.
你想要脫離其中
So maybe you do what you gotta do to get out.
也許這就是你成為心理醫生的原因
You know, maybe you became a psychologist.
答對了  就是這樣  讓我做事吧  你妨礙我了
Bingo. That's it. Let me do my job now. You start with me. Come on.
-也許你娶錯女人  -也許你講話該小心點
-Maybe you married the wrong woman. -Maybe you should watch your mouth!
小心點  好嗎
Watch it right there, chief, all right?
啊
Ah.
情況就是如此  是嗎
That's it, isn't it?
你娶錯女人了
You married the wrong woman.
發生什麼事  她拋棄你了
What happened? What, did she leave you?
她是不是...搞上別的男人
Was she, you know... banging some other guy?
再對我太太無禮  我就宰了你
If you ever disrespect my wife again, I will end you.
我會他媽的宰了你
I will fucking end you.
聽到沒
Got that, chief?
時間到了
Time's up.
是的
Yeah.
稍息  兩位
At ease, gentlemen.
你沒事吧
You okay?
如果你不再想見他  我理解
Look, I'll understand if you don't wanna meet with him again.
星期四下午四點  一定要他來
Thursday, 4:00. Make sure the kid's here.
好
Yeah.
謝謝
Thanks.
你戴那副眼鏡好可愛
Well, you look lovely in those glasses.
-多謝你  -真漂亮
-Thank you very much. -They're just beautiful.
-我一直想擦藍色眼影  -美極了
-Yes, I always wanted dark blue eye shadow. -Wonderful.
我在英國長大  念貴族學校
Growing up in England, you know, I went to a very nice school.
就是那種積極  有組織
You know, it was kind of progressive, organic,
又獨立自主的私立學校
do-it-yourself, private school.
然後是很有前途的哈佛醫學院
Then Harvard. Hopefully med school.
你知道我發現什麼
You know, I figured out, by the end,
最後我的腦子會價值25萬美金
my braings gonna be worth $250,000.
聽起來很可怕吧
That sounded horrible, didn't it?
再來一杯"邁泰"
Bring me another mai tai!
酷  你父母一定很樂於付錢
Yeah, that's cool. I mean, I bet your parents were happy to pay.
錯  我自己付  我繼承了遺產
No, I was happy to pay. I inherited the money.
那麼錢都給哈佛嗎
Wow. Is Harvard getting all that money?
不  給了斯坦福  我六月畢業後到那裡深造
No, Stanford. I'm going there in June when I graduate.
所以你只是想利用這個水手囉
All right, so you just wanted to use this sailor and then run away, huh?
我要先拿你做解剖實驗
I was gonna, you know, experiment on you for anatomy class first, obviously.
這樣的話  好吧
In that case, that's fine.
-想看我變魔術嗎  -好啊
-Hey, you wanna see my magic tricks, Skylar? -Of course.
好  保證...
All right. Promise to...
好的
All right.
這是給你的  魯道夫
This one's for you, Rudolph.
等等  你需要我的魔杖
Wait, wait. You need my wand.
好  敲一下  謝謝  好的
All right, give me a hit. Thank you. All right.
我會讓這些焦糖消失
I'm gonna make all these caramels disappear.
準備好了嗎
You ready? Ready.
一  二  三
One, two, three.
全不見了
They're all gone.
有兔子的話...會比較成功
That was my... It works better when I have my rabbit.
那...
Well...
我不常約會
I don't really date, you know, that much.
我認為自己...多不幸
How very unfortunate... I think for me.
你懂我意思  我知道你在想什麼
You know what I mean? I know you've been thinking about it.
-我沒有  -我知道你有
-Oh, no, I haven't. -Yes, you have.
真的沒有
No, I really haven't.
你有  你想要睡前一吻
Yes, you have. You were hoping to get a good night kiss.
不  我想要睡前一炮
No, you know, I tell ya, I was hoping to get a good night laid.
不過我願意勉強接受一吻
But I'll settle for, like, a kiss, you know?
-你很高尚  -謝謝
-How very noble of you. -Thank you.
-嗯  -不  我...我真的想要一吻
-Mm. -No, I was... I was hoping for a kiss.
何不現在就解決
Well, why don't we just get it out of the way now?
-現在  -對
-Right now? -Yeah.
來
Come on.
我吃到你的酸黃瓜了
I think I got some of your pickle.
又是你
You again, huh?
跟我來
Come with me.
現在要幹嘛  這是男人的行家選擇
So what's this? A Taster's Choice moment between guys?
這裡真不錯  你喜歡天鵝  這算戀物癖嗎
This is really nice. You got a thing for swans? Is this, like, a fetish?
這是需要花點時間的事嗎
Is it something, like, maybe we need to devote some time to?
-我在想你批評我畫的事  -噢
-Thought about what you said to me the other day. About my painting. -Oh.
失眠大半夜的思索後
Stayed up half the night thinking about it.
突然我想到一件事
Something occurred to me.
接著就沉沉入睡  不再想你的事
I fell into a deep, peaceful sleep and haven't thought about you since.
-你知道我當時想到什麼嗎  -不知道
-You know what occurred to me? -No.
你只是個孩子  你根本不曉得你在說什麼
You're just a kid. You don't have the faintest idea what you're talking about.
-為什麼  謝謝  -沒關係
-Why, thank you. -It's all right.
因你沒離開過波士頓
You've never been out of Boston.
是沒有
Nope.
所以問你藝術  你可能會...
So if I asked you about art, you'd probably give me the skinny...
提出藝術書籍中的粗淺論調
on every art book ever written.
有關米開朗基羅  你知道很多
Michelangelo? You know a lot about him.
他的政治抱負  他和教皇
Life's work, political aspirations. Him and the pope.
性傾向  所有作品  對嗎
Sexual orientation. The whole works, right?
但你不知道西斯汀教堂的氣味
I bet you can't tell me what it smells like in the Sistine Chapel.
你從沒站在那兒觀賞美麗的天花板
You never actually stood there and looked up at that beautiful ceiling.
我看過
Seeing that.
如果我問關於女人的事
If I ask you about women,
你八成會說出個人偏好的謬論
you'll probably give me a syllabus of your personal favorites.
你可能上過幾次床
You may have even been laid a few times.
但你說不出在女人身旁醒來...
But you can't tell me what it feels like to wake up next to a woman...
那種很幸福的滋味
and feel truly happy.
你是個很倔的孩子
You're a tough kid.
我問戰爭  你會說莎士比亞的話
I ask you about war, you'd probably throw Shakespeare at me, right?
"共赴戰場  親愛的朋友"
"Once more into the breach, dear friends."
但你從沒接近過戰爭
But you've never been near one.
從沒把好友的頭抱在膝蓋上...
You've never held your best friend's head in your lap...
看著他吐出最後一口氣向你呼救
and watch him gasp his last breath looking to you for help.
我若問你愛情  你會引述十四行詩
If I asked you about love, you'd probably quote me a sonnet,
但你從沒看過女人的脆弱
but you've never looked at a woman and been totally vulnerable.
她能以雙眼擊倒你
Known someone that could level you with her eyes.
感覺上帝讓天使為你下凡
Feeling like God put an angel on Earth just for you,
她能從地獄救出你
who could rescue you from the depths of hell.
你不瞭解當她天使的滋味
And you wouldn't know what it's like to be her angel,
擁有對她的愛  直到永遠
to have that love for her be there forever.
經歷這一切  經歷癌症
Through anything. Through cancer.
你無法體會在醫院躺兩個月...
And you wouldn't know about sleeping sitting up in a hospital room...
握住她的纖纖小手那種感覺
for two months, holding her hand,
因為醫生一看到你就知道...
because the doctors could see in your eyes...
會客時間的規定對你無效
that the terms "visiting hours" don't apply to you.
你不瞭解真正的失去
You don't know about real loss,
因為唯有愛別人勝於自己才能體會
because that only occurs when you love something more than you love yourself.
我懷疑你敢那樣愛人
I doubt you've ever dared to love anybody that much.
看著你  我沒看到聰明自信
I look at you. I don't see an intelligent, confident man.
我看到被嚇傻的狂妄孩子
I see a cocky, scared shitless kid.
但你是天才  沒人能否認
But you're a genius, Will. No one denies that.
沒人能瞭解你的深度
No one could possibly understand the depths of you.
但你看我的畫就認定瞭解我
But you presume to know everything about me because you saw a painting of mine.
你把我的人生撕裂了
You ripped my fucking life apart.
你是孤兒  對吧
You're an orphan, right?
你想我會知道你日子有多苦...
Do you think I'd know the first thing about how hard your life has been...
你的感受  你是誰...
how you feel, who you are...
是因為我看過霧都孤兒嗎
because I read Oliver Twist?
太簡化你了嗎
Does that encapsulate you?
我不在乎  因為...
Personally, I don't give a shit about all that, because...
你知道嗎  我對你無從下手...
You know what? I can't learn anything from you...
我不能靠任何書籍認識你
I can't read in some fucking book.
除非你想談自己
Unless you wanna talk about you,
談你是誰
who you are.
那我就著迷了  我願意加入
And I'm fascinated. I'm in.
但你不想那麼做  對嗎
But you don't wanna do that, do you, sport?
你怕你會被說出來的話嚇到
You're terrified of what you might say.
輪到你說了  大哥
Your move, chief.
喂  喂
Hello? Hello?
喂
Hello?
瓦蘭帝教授  又是你嗎
Professor Valenti, are you calling me again?
怪胎
Freak.
-上帝  -天哪  你打給誰
-Oh, God. -Christ, who did you call?
-沒有  我忘了號碼  -你他媽智障
-No one. I forgot the number. -You fucking retarded?
冒雨打電話  竟忘了號碼
You went all the way out there in the rain, and you didn't bring the number.
那是你媽的免費電話
No, it was your mother's 900 number. I just ran out of quarters.
別扯上我媽好不  我剛上過你媽
Why don't we get off on mothers? I just got off yours.
很好笑  摩根
That's pretty funny, Morgan.
太炫了
That's a fucking nickel, bitch.
-繼續跟我作對看看  -好的  那麼  摩根
-Keep antagonizing me. Watch what happens. -All right, then, Morgan.
-看看會怎樣  -好的  那麼  摩根
-Watch what happens. -All right, then, Morgan.
再整我啊
Keep fucking with me.
不准抽煙
No smoking.
什麼叫沒講話  你在那裡一個鐘頭
What do you mean, he didn't talk? You were in there for an hour.
他就坐著等會談結束
He just sat there counting the seconds until the session was over.
-讓人印象蠻深刻的  -他為什麼要那麼做
-Pretty impressive, actually. -Why would he do that?
證明他不想講就不必講
To prove to me he doesn't have to talk to me if he doesn't want to.
這是小孩玩的
What is this? Some kind of staring contest
瞪人比賽嗎
between two kids from the old neighborhood?
對  而且我不能先講話
Yeah, it is, and I can't talk first.
我們知道你的理論  亞歷山大
We know your theory, Alexander,
但這孩子找出簡單的幾何圖
but the boy's found a simple geometrical picture.
-樹狀結構行不通  -他把兩個頂點連起來了
-A tree structure won't work. -Look now. He's joining the two vertices.
但我算出總數
But I can do the sum.
-那是集合項的方法  -但是  傑洛
-It's how you group the terms, Alexander. -But, Gerry.
如果這樣做...
If we do the whole thing this way, then...
看  看
Hey, look, look.
我寫下來了  這樣比較簡單
I wrote it down. It's simpler this way.
有些人就是走運
Sometimes people get lucky.
你是個聰明的人
You're a brilliant man.
我有一次搭飛機
You know, I was on this plane once,
坐在機上...
and I'm sitting there, and...
機長廣播道
the captain gets on, he does his whole, you know,
"飛行于三萬五千尺"  但是他放下麥克風後
"we'll be cruising at 35,000 feet," but then he puts the mike down.
-他忘了把它關掉  -嗯
-He forgets to turn it off. -Mm-hmm.
他轉向副駕駛說
So he turns to the copilot. He's, like,
"我現在很想要口交和咖啡"
"You know, all I could use right now is a fucking blow job and a cup of coffee."
空服員沖去駕駛室...
So the stewardess fucking goes bombing up from the back of the plane...
跟他說麥克風沒關
to tell him the microphone's still on.
機尾有個人說"別忘了咖啡"
This guy in the back of the plane's like, "Hey, hon, don't forget the coffee."
你搭過飛機
You ever been on a plane?
沒有  那只是個笑話
No, but it's a fucking joke.
用第一人稱比較好笑
It works better if I tell it in the first person.
沒錯
Yeah, it does.
我做過愛  知道嗎
I have been laid, you know?
真的  很好
Really? Good for you.
-我很厲害  -很厲害
-Big time, big time. -Big time, huh?
對  我上禮拜有約會
I went on a date last week.
-怎麼樣  -很好
-How'd it go? -It was good.
-要再約會嗎  -不知道
-Going out again? -I don't know.
-為什麼  -我沒打給她
-Why? -Haven't called her.
-天哪  你真外行  -我知道我在幹嘛
-Christ, you're an amateur. -I know what I'm doing.
放心  我知道我在幹嘛
Yeah. Don't worry about me. I know what I'm doing.
這女孩很漂亮
Yeah, but this girl was, like, you know, beautiful.
她聰明風趣  跟我以前認識的女生不一樣
She's smart. She's fun. She's different from most of the girls I've been with.
那就打給她  羅密歐
So call her up, Romeo.
讓自己發現她並沒那麼聰明嗎
Why, so I can realize she's not that smart.
其實很無聊嗎  我是說  你別...
That she's fucking boring? You know, I mean, you don't...
這女孩現在很完美  我不想破壞這種完美
This girl's, like, fucking perfect right now. I don't wanna ruin that.
或許是你不想破壞你自己的完美
Maybe you're perfect right now. Maybe you don't wanna ruin that.
我覺得那是極好的哲學
But I think that's a super philosophy, Will.
這樣可以
That way, you can go
一輩子不認識任何人
through your entire life without ever having to really know anybody.
我太太一緊張就放屁
My wife used to fart when she was nervous.
她有各種奇妙的小特質
She had all sorts of wonderful idiosyncrasies.
你知道  她睡覺會放屁
You know, she used to fart in her sleep.
抱歉跟你講這種事
Just thought I'd share that with you.
有天晚上大聲到把狗吵醒
One night it was so loud, it woke the dog up.
她醒來說"是你嗎"
She woke up and gone, like, "Was that you?"
我說"是"  我不忍心告訴她  天哪
I said, "Yeah." I didn't have the heart to tell her. Oh, God.
-她把自己臭醒  -是的
-She woke herself up? -Yes.
天哪  她去世兩年了
Oh, Christ. But, Will, she's been dead two years
而那是我記得的事
and that's the shit I remember.
像那樣的小事很奇妙
It's wonderful stuff, you know? Little things like that.
那是我最想念的事
Yeah, but those are the things I miss the most.
這些小特質
Those little idiosyncrasies that only I knew about.
讓她成為我太太
That's what made her my wife.
她也知道我所有的小瑕疵
Boy, and she had the goods on me too. She knew all my little peccadillos.
人們稱之為不完美  其實不然
People call these things "imperfections," but they're not.
那才是好東西
That's the good stuff.
能選擇讓誰進入我們的世界
And then we get to choose who we let into our weird little worlds.
你並不完美
You're not perfect, sport.
我不吊你胃口
And let me save you the suspense.
你認識的女生也不完美
This girl you met, she isn't perfect either.
問題是你們是否完美地合適
But the question is whether or not you're perfect for each other.
親密關係就是這麼回事
That's the whole deal. That's what intimacy is all about.
你可以知道全世界的事
Now you can know everything in the world, sport,
但發掘的方法唯有去嘗試
but the only way you're finding out that one is by giving it a shot.
你不能跟我這個糟老頭學
You certainly won't learn from an old fucker like me.
就算我知道  我也不告訴你
Even if I did know, I wouldn't tell a pissant like you.
為什麼
Yeah, why not?
你把其他事都告訴我了  天哪
You told me every other fucking thing. Jesus Christ.
你的話比我所遇到的任何心理醫生都多
Fucking talk more than any shrink I ever seen in my life.
我只是教心理學  我說過我不是心理醫生
I teach the shit. I didn't say I knew how to do it.
是的
Yeah.
那麼你想過再婚嗎
You ever think about getting remarried?
我太太死了
My wife's dead.
-所以才叫"再婚"  -她死了
-Hence the word "remarried." -She's dead.
我想那是極好的哲學  尚恩
Yeah, well, I think that's a super philosophy, Sean.
這樣可以過下半輩子...
I mean, that way, you can actually go through the rest of your life...
而不用認識任何人
without ever really knowing anybody.
時間到了
Time's up.
-別關  -好的
-Hold it open. -Okay.
謝謝
Thanks.
G小調  最悲歎的曲調
"G" minor seventh. Saddest of all chords.
-哈羅  -嗨
-Hello. -Hey.
你去哪裡了
Where have you been?
對不起  我...我很忙...
I'm sorry. I've been, like... I've been really busy, and...
-但是...-我也是
-But, um... -Mmm. Me too.
我還...以為你會打來
Yeah. I... I thought you'd call.
是...
Yeah, um...
-我是說  我們相處愉快  -的確如此
-I mean, we had a really good time. -I had a really good time too.
我是說...我...
I mean, I just... I...
對不起  我搞砸了
I'm sorry, you know. I blew it.
不  沒關係
No. No, I mean, you know, it's all right.
我在想  呃
Yeah, um, so, I was wondering if, uh,
你會不會再讓我試一遍
if, you know, you'd give me another crack at it.
我是說  讓我再約你出去
You know, let me take you out again.
-不行  -好吧
-I can't. -All right.
不  我...我不是說永遠不行
Oh, no, I didn't... I didn't mean I can't, like, ever.
只是說現在不行
I just can't right now.
我得做質子光譜分配
I've got to assign the proton spectrum for "ebogamine."
聽起來有趣  其實很無聊
All that sounds really, really interesting. It's actually fantastically boring.
-好吧  呃...-或許改天吧
-All right, um... -Maybe some other time.
-那明天呢  -好啊
-Like tomorrow? -Um, yeah, all right.
-好的  -好的
-Okay. -Okay.
-再見  -再見
-Bye. -Bye.
你在這兒幹嘛
What are you doing here?
我等不到明天了
I couldn't wait till tomorrow.
你從哪兒弄到這個
Where the fuck did you get this?
我得跟你同學上床
I had to sleep with someone in your class.
希望是個穿拖鞋又有口臭的人
Oh, I hope it was someone with the open-toed sandals and the really bad breath.
-走  去找樂子  -不行  我得念這個
-Come on. Let's go have some fun. -No, I've got to learn this.
你不會明天就要開刀吧
Well, you're not going into surgery tomorrow, are you?
-不是  -走吧
-No. -Let's go.
天啊  我的狗贏了
Oh, my God! My dog is winning!
加油  迷霧
Come on, Misty!
加油  快跑  看  加油
Come on! Run! Look at that! Come on!
他在那邊  迷霧領先  加油
Look, there he goes. Misty, run! Come on!
-我們贏了  -它完勝對手
-We won. -He totally won.
你在這邊長大的嗎
So did you grow up around here then?
不遠  南波士頓
Not far. South Boston.
贏了比賽讓我臉好熱
Still glowing from my win.
看你樂成這樣
Look at you. You're so happy.
我的樣子還好吧
And what was that like then?
很正常  沒什麼特別的
It was normal, I guess. Nothing special.
你有很多兄弟姊妹嗎
Do you got lots of brothers and sisters?
-你有很多兄弟姊妹嗎  -那是我問你的
-Do I have a lot of brothers and sisters? -That's what I said.
-我是個天主教徒  你說呢  -對
-Well, Irish Catholic, what do you think? -Right. That's right.
-幾個  -告訴你你也不信
-How many? -You wouldn't believe me if I told you.
-為什麼  說啊  五個  -不是
-Why? Go on. What? Five? -No.
七個  八個  幾個
Seven? Eight? How many?
-我有十二個哥哥  -你才沒有
-I have 12 big brothers. -You do not!
我發誓  我是幸運十三
No, I swear to God. I swear to God. I'm lucky 13 right here.
你知道他們的名字嗎
Do you know all their names?
當然知道  他們是我哥哥
Do I... Yeah, they're my brothers.
叫什麼名字
What are they called?
馬奇  瑞奇  丹尼  泰瑞
Marky, Ricky, Danny, Terry,
麥奇  大衛  提米
Mikey, Davey, Timmy,
湯米  喬依  羅比  強尼和布萊恩
Tommy, Joey, Robby, Johnny and Brian.
再說一遍
Say it again.
馬奇  瑞奇  丹尼  泰瑞
Marky, Ricky, Danny, Terry,
麥奇  大衛  提米
Mikey, Davey, Timmy,
湯米  喬依  羅比  強尼和布萊恩
Tommy, Joey, Robby, Johnny and Brian.
還有小威
And Willy.
-小威  -對
-Willy? -Yeah.
-威爾  -哇
-Will. -Wow.
-你常和他們見面嗎  -他們都住南區
-Do you still see all of them? -Yeah, well, they all live in Southie.
-我跟他們中三個人一起住  -是嗎
-I'm living with three of them right now. -Oh, yeah?
-是的  -我好想見他們
-Yeah. -I'd like to meet them.
好  就去見他們
Yeah, we'll do that.
我昨晚讀過你的書
Oh, you know, I read your book last night.
原來是你
Oh, so you're the one.
你還輔導退伍軍人嗎
Do you still, uh... Do you still counsel veterans?
沒有
No, I don't.
-為什麼  -我太太生病時就沒做了
-Why not? -Well, I gave it up when my wife got sick.
你有沒有想過若沒遇見你太太
You ever wonder what your life would be like if you,
你的生活會怎樣
uh, if you never met your wife?
什麼  沒有她會不會比較好
What? Wonder if I'd be better off without her?
-不  不  不  我沒說比較好  -不
-No, no, no, I'm not saying, like, better off. -No.
-我沒那意思  -沒關係  這是很重要的問題
-I didn't mean it like that. -It's all right. It's an important question.
因為人總會有不好的時候  但這也會讓你...
because you'll have bad times, but that'll always wake you up...
回憶起從前不曾在意的好事
to the good stuff you weren't paying attention to.
你不後悔認識你太太
And you don't regret meeting your wife?
為什麼  因為我現在的痛苦
Why? because the pain I feel now?
是有遺憾  但我不後悔跟她共度的每一天
Oh, I got regrets, Will, but I don't regret a single day I spent with her.
你幾時知道她是理想對象
So when did you know, like, that she was the one for you?
1975年10月21日
October 21, 1975.
天哪  你他媽的記得日期
Jesus Christ. You know the fucking day?
對  那是世界大賽第六場
Oh, yeah, because it was game six of the World Series,
紅襪隊史上最重大的球賽
biggest game in Red Sox history.
-沒錯  -我和朋友睡人行道排隊買票
-Yeah, sure. -My friends and I had slept out all night to get tickets.
-你有票  -對  比賽當天我們坐在酒吧
-You got tickets? -Yep. Day of the game I was sitting in a bar,
等球賽開始  有個女孩走進來
waiting for the game to start and in walks this girl.
那是場很棒的球賽  八局下半
It was an amazing game though. You know, bottom of the eighth, Carbo ties it up.
六比六平手  打到第十二局
It was 6-6. It went to 12.
下半場時矮冬瓜菲克斯上場
Bottom of the 12th, in stepped Carlton Fisk, old Pudge.
他站上本壘  姿勢很怪
Steps up to the plate. You know, he's got that weird stance.
-嗯  嗯  -然後...砰  他把球打擊出去
-Yeah, yeah. -And then... Boom! He clocks it, you know.
左外野高飛球
High fly ball down the left field line!
三萬五千人站起來對球吼
Thirty-five thousand people on their feet, yelling at the ball.
這還不算什麼  因為菲斯克像發了瘋似地揮手說
But that's nothing, because Fisk, he's waving at the ball like a madman.
-對  我見到過  -"飛過去  飛過去
-Yeah, I've seen that. -"Get over! Get over!
-對  -飛過去"
-Right. -Get over!"
結果球飛到邊界  三萬五千名球迷...
Then it hits the foul pole. He goes ape-shit, and 35,000 fans...
沖到場上
They charge the field, you know.
他大叫來開闢道路
Yeah, and he's fucking blowing people outta the way.
"大家讓開  大家讓開"
"Get outta the way! Get outta the way!"
我真不敢相信你有票
I can't fucking believe you had tickets to that fucking game!
你有沖到場上嗎
Did you rush the field?
我沒沖到場上  我不在場
No, I didn't rush the fucking field. I wasn't there.
-什麼  -我跟我未來的老婆在喝酒
-What? -No, I was in a bar, having a drink with my future wife.
你錯過菲斯克的全壘打
You missed Pudge Fisk's home run to have a fucking drink
跟一個不認識的女人喝酒
with some lady you never met?
對  你該看看她  令人驚豔
Yeah, but you should have seen her. She was a stunner.
-我才不管他媽的...-她讓整個屋子亮起來
-I don't care if... -Oh, no, no, she lit up the room.
-西施走進來我也不在乎  -哦  西施
-I don't care if Helen of Troy walks into the room. -Oh, Helen of Troy!
那可是重量級比賽啊  天哪
That's game six! Oh, my God,
你朋友都是些什麼人
and who were these friends of yours?
-他們就這麼放過你  -他們沒辦法
-They let you get away with that? -They had to.
-你跟他們怎麼說  -我把票滑過去
-What did you say to them? -I just slid my ticket across the table.
說"抱歉  兄弟們  我要去找一個女孩"
I said, "Sorry, guys. I gotta see about a girl."
-"我要去找一個女孩"  -是的
-"I gotta go see about a girl"? -Yes!
你就那麼說  他們就放過你了
That's what you said? They let you get away with that?
對  他們看到我認真的眼睛
Oh, yeah. They saw it in my eyes that I meant it.
-你騙我  -不  我沒騙你
-You're kidding me? -No, I'm not kidding you, Will.
所以我現在不會因為...
That's why I'm not talking right now about some girl I saw at a bar 20 years ago...
當年在酒吧沒和她說話而懊悔終生
and how I always regretted not going over and talking to her.
我不後悔跟南茜結褵的18年
I don't regret the 18 years I was married to Nancy.
不後悔為她的病放棄輔導
I don't regret the six years I had to give up counseling when she got sick,
不後悔那最後幾年守著重病的她
and I don't regret the last years when she got really sick.
更不會後悔錯過球賽
And I sure as hell don't regret missing a damn game.
只是有點遺憾
That's regret.
哇
Wow!
看到那場球賽還是不錯的
Would have been nice to catch that game though.
我不曉得矮冬瓜會擊出全壘打
I didn't know Pudge was gonna hit a home run.
我在球場上很有優勢
You know, I'm very, very useful on the court.
我很高
I'm extremely tall.
-你沒那麼高  -我會灌籃
-You're not that tall. -I dunk.
我能打NBA嗎
Will I ever play in the N.B.A.?
"絕對可以"
"It is decidedly so." Hmph.
為什麼老是待在這邊
Why do we always stay here?
因為比我家好
because it's nicer than my place.
但我從沒去過你家
Yes, but I've never seen your place.
我知道
I know.
我幾時見到你朋友和哥哥
When am I gonna meet your friends and your brothers?
嗯  他們不常來這裡
Well, they don't really come down here that much.
我可以到南波士頓
I think I can make it to South Boston.
有點遠
It's kind of a hike.
是我還是他們見不得人
Is it me you're hiding from them or the other way around?
-好  我們去  -幾時
-All right, we'll go. -When?
不知道  下個禮拜吧
I don't know. We'll go sometime next week.
如過我說不讓我見他們
What if I said I would not sleep
就再也不跟你上床  你怎麼辦
with you again until you let me meet your friends?
我會說  清晨四點半  他們應該醒了
I'd say it's, like, 4:30 in the morning. They're probably up.
天哪  男人真無恥
Oh, my God. Men are shameless.
你們男人就只會
If you're not thinking with your wiener,
用小弟弟思考
then you're acting directly on its behalf.
僅代表我的小弟弟  向否向你預支
You bet. And on behalf of my wiener, can I get an advance payment?
不知道  我問問"前途不明朗"
I don't know. Let's ask. "Outlook does not look good."
-什麼  -幹...嘿  查克  沒事  繼續睡
-What? -Fuck the... Hey, Chuck. No. Nothing. Go back to sleep.
"前途"  你去打NBA才前途不明朗
"Outlook"? That's the same thing that told you you was gonna play in the N.B.A.
沒錯  所以你最好開始買季票
Exactly, so look out. You'd better start buying some season tickets.
正有此意  我很高  我喜歡穿短褲
Mmm! I plan to. I'm tall. I like wearing shorts.
勾射  勾射  灌籃  灌籃
Hook, hook. Dunk, dunk.
-你沒那麼高  -我有
-You're not that tall. -Yes, I am.
我三分射籃很行
Maybe I'm all about three points.
我就很會打全壘打
I'm all about home runs.
別用運動術語影射
Stop mixing your sporting metaphors.
妖精的老二在猴子屁眼裡
A leprechaun's got his dick in the monkey's ass.
摩根跑出來說"我不介意  我不介意..."
Morgan comes running in, going, "I don't mind it. I don't mind..."
幹  你竟挑我們
Well, I can't believe you brought Skylar here
爛醉時帶她來
when we're fucking all bombed and drinking.
我知道  摩根  我們很難得一起喝酒
I know, Morgan. It's a real rarity we'd be all drinking.
我叔叔馬帝只要一喝酒  就會狂歡個一年半載
My uncle Marty drinks. He'll go on a bender for six, eight months.
我講過他開車
Did I ever tell ya what happened to him
被攔下來的事沒
when he was driving up there and got pulled over?
-我跟你們講過的  對嗎  -馬帝  嗯
-I told you guys, right? -Marty, yeah.
我來說說馬帝叔叔的事  你們應該知道的
Let me tell ya what happened to my uncle Marty, because you oughta know this.
他很喜歡講故事  每次我到他那裡都有新花樣
He's always telling stories. Every time we come here he's got another story.
這個我們早就聽過了  還是說吧  快講
But we all heard this one. Go ahead. Say it anyway.
我會講  多謝  換我發言
I will go ahead. Thanks a lot. Guess I have the floor now.
我叔叔開車回家  對嗎
My uncle Marty's driving home, right?
撞到了樹  對嗎
Bombed out of his tree, right?
他醉得一塌糊塗  撞得七零八落
Just hammered out of his gourd. Just wrecked.
州警看見  把他攔下來  我叔叔慘了
This state trooper sees him, pulls him over. So my uncle's fucked basically.
州警要他下車走直線
Got him out of the car, trying to make him walk the line.
結果他吐在州警身上
He gets out of the car, pukes,
州警確信他超過酒精濃度
and the statie's pretty sure he's over the legal limit.
正要把他戴上手銬送去坐牢
So he's about to throw the cuffs on him and put him in jail.
突然五十碼外他媽的一聲巨響
All of a sudden, 50 yards down the road, there's this huge fucking boom.
-州警嚇一大跳  轉身...-槍聲
-Statie gets real spooked. He turns around... -He got shot?
不是...你聽過這故事了
No. So... So... You heard this story before.
摩根  停  停
Yeah, Morgan, stop. Stop.
是別人的車撞到樹  出事了
Some other guy's car had hit a tree. There was an accident.
總之...
Anyway...
-那他...-他媽的閉嘴
-How could he hear... -Shut the fuck up!
-你把他惹毛了  -我要扭斷你脖子  閉嘴
-You're driving him nuts. -I'm gonna break your neck. Shut up!
他跟你說過這故事了
He told you the story once before.
州警跟我叔叔說"站住  別走"
So he tells my uncle, "Stay here. Don't move."
就跑去處理另一起事故
Statie goes running down the road to deal with the other accident.
躺在尿和嘔吐物中幾分鐘後
After a few minutes of just lying in his own piss and vomit,
我叔叔才想到他在那兒幹嘛
my uncle starts wondering what he's doing there.
於是站起來開車回家
Gets up, gets in his car and just drives home.
隔天早上我叔叔還昏迷不醒
The next morning my uncle's just passed out.
他聽到敲門聲
He hears this knocking at the door.
下樓拉開門...說"什麼事"
So he goes downstairs, pulls the door open... "What?"
敲門的是攔下他的州警
It's the state trooper that pulled him over.
州警說"我操  你明知故問
Statie says, "Fuck you mean, 'What?'
我昨晚攔下你  你逃走了"
You know what. I pulled you over last night is what, and you took off."
叔叔說"我從來沒見過你
He's like, "l never seen you before in my life.
我整晚在家  你亂講什麼"
I've been home all night with my kids. I don't know who the fuck you are."
州警說"別裝蒜了  到車庫"
He's like, "You know who I am. Let me get in your garage."
我叔叔說"什麼"  州警說"帶我去你的車庫"
My uncle's like, "What?" He said, "You heard me. Let me get in your garage."
我叔叔說"好的"  帶他到車庫  打開門
He was like, "All right. Fine." Takes him out to the garage, opens the door.
警車就在我叔叔的車庫裡
And there's... The statie's police cruiser is in my uncle's garage.
他他媽的...
He was so fucking...
他醉到他媽的開錯車回家了
He was so fucking hammered he drove the wrong car home.
最屌的是州警好糗...
The best part about it is, the fucking state trooper...
他整晚什麼都沒做
was so embarrassed he didn't do anything.
開著我叔叔的車挨家挨戶找人
He'd been driving around all night in my uncle's Chevelle, looking for the house.
你的故事重點是什麼
All right, Chuck, what the fuck is the point of your story?
他逃跑了就是重點
He got away. That's the point.
-好  問題是...-得了  快停下
-Well, question... -Come on. Stop.
-我在努力闡明一些事情  -你是在糗他
-I'm trying to clarify something. -You're embarrassing him.
-你講的故事沒什麼道理  -這個故事有道理
-It doesn't make any sense. -It does make sense,
聽故事別問東問西的
if you listen to the story and quit asking questions.
摩根  看這個故事你懂不懂
Well, let's see if you can get this one. I've got a little story for you.
好  一對老夫妻在床上  瑪麗和派帝
All right, there's an old couple in bed, Mary and Paddie.
結婚50周年那天他們醒來
They wake up on the morning of their 50th anniversary.
瑪麗深情地望著派帝
Mary looks over and gazes adoringly at Paddie.
說"天哪  派帝
She's like, "Oh, Jesus, Paddie.
你真是一個大帥哥  我愛你
You're such a good-looking feller. I love ya.
我要送你一件禮物
I want to give ya a little present.
你渴望什麼我都給你
Anything your little heart desires, I'm going to give it to ya.
你想要什麼
What would ya like?
派帝說"瑪麗  這真是甜蜜的提議
Paddie's like, "Oh, gee, Mary. That's a very sweet offer.
五十年來就少一樣東西
Now, in 50 years, there's one thing that's been missing,
我希望你幫我吹喇叭
and, uh, I would like you to give me a blow job.
我想要"  瑪麗說"好"
I would like for it." Mary's like, "All right."
她把假牙拿掉  放進杯子裡  然後幫他吹
She takes her teeth out, puts them in the glass. She gives him a blow job.
之後派帝說"天啊  這就是我最渴望
Afterwards, Paddie's like, "Yeah, geez, now that's what I've been missing.
最美妙  最勾魂攝魄的事
That was the most beautiful, earth-shattering thing ever!
太棒了  瑪麗  我愛你
Beautiful, Mary! I love ya!
我能為你做什麼嗎"
Is there anything that I can do for you?"
瑪麗抬頭看著他說"親一下"
Mary looks up to him and she goes, "Give us a kiss."
-噢  -噢  我的天
-Oh! -Oh, my God!
-好噁心  -不噁心  我聽過更噁心的
-That's filthy. -It's not that filthy. I've heard filthy.
-離我遠點  -好的  再見
-Get off of me! -All right. See you guys later.
保重  比利
All right. Take it easy, Bill.
史凱蘭  謝謝你過來
So, Skylar, thanks for coming by.
改變我對哈佛人的看法
Changed my opinion of Harvard people.
別驟下斷語  他們跟我不同
You don't want to rush to judgment on that one, because they're not all like me.
我相信  很高興認識你
Oh. I'm sure. It was nice to meet ya.
-噢  -小心  慢慢讓開
-Oh. -Take it easy. Slowly back away.
-快點  兄弟  -我不知道你要幹什麼  老兄
-Oh, come on. Brother. -I don't know what you're doing, dude.
-你要送我們  -你以為我在幹嘛
-You're giving us a ride. -What the fuck do I look like to you?
-快點  查克  -你來步行  車給威爾
-Come on, Chuck. -You're walking, bitch. Will's taking the car.
好  謝了  很感激
All right, thanks, sucker. I appreciate it.
幹嘛這麼正經
I don't know what you're getting all serious about.
-你還是要先送我回家  -這樣很不順路
-You're dropping me off first. -It's really out of the way.
別以為今晚可以外宿...
Oh, okay. Just because you don't have to sleep in your one-room palace tonight...
就屌成這樣
don't start thinking you're bad.
等一下  你說要去看你家
Hey, wait a minute. You said we were gonna see your place.
-今晚不行  -今晚不行  哪一晚都不行
-Not tonight. -Oh, no, not tonight. Not any other night.
他知道你一看過就會甩了他
He knows once you see that shit-hole he's getting dropped like a bad habit.
但我想見你哥哥
But I wanted to meet your brothers.
不  改天吧
We're gonna do that another time.
好吧
All right.
我需要鑰匙
Need them keys.
空服員聽到就往走道上沖
The stewardess hears this and goes hauling ass down the aisle.
我喊道"別忘了咖啡"
I yell, "Don't forget the coffee."
狗屁  你沒那麼說
No shit! You didn't say that.
拜託  那是笑話嘛
For Christ's sake, Marty, it's a joke.
-我認識真的碰到這事的人  -只是個笑話
-I know someone that actually happened to, Marty. -A joke.
-傑洛  -嗨
-Gerry. -Hi.
-這邊很難找嗎  -不會  我搭計程車
-Have trouble finding the place? -No, I took a cab.
提米  這是傑洛  大學同學
Timmy, this is Gerry. We went to college together.
你好  幸會
How you doing? Nice to meet ya.
-幸會  -請你喝杯啤酒吧
-Pleased to meet you. -Can I get you a beer?
不  來杯沛綠雅
Um, no, just a Perrier.
那是法文的蘇打水
That's French for club soda.
-蘇打水  好  -再來幾個三明治
-Club soda, yeah. -Couple of sandwiches too.
-好  -算在我帳上
-Sure. -Put it on my tab.
你打算要簽帳嗎
You ever planning on paying your tab?
要  我這邊有中獎彩券
Yeah, chief, got the winning lottery ticket right here.
-獎金多少  -一千兩百萬
-What's the jackpot? -Twelve million.
-我看不夠付  -夠付你的變性手術了
-I don't think that'll cover it. -It'll cover your sex change operation.
-堅果  -不  謝謝
-Nuts? -No, thank you.
那麼  你想談談威爾
So, you wanted to talk about Will.
-好像很順利  -我想是的
-Well, it seems to be going well. -I think so.
你跟他談過未來沒
Have you talked to him at all about his future?
沒談到那種程度  我們還只是在往事中徘徊
No, we haven't gotten into that yet. We're still banging away at the past.
該開始談了  許多工作都急著找他
Maybe you should. My phone's been ringing off the hook with job offers.
-哪種工作  -尖端科技數學  智囊團
-What kind? -Cutting edge mathematics, think tanks.
威爾的頭腦能發揮的地方
The kind of place where a mind like Will's is given free rein.
那真好  但他還沒準備好
That's great that there are offers, but I don't really think he's ready for that.
我想你不明白  尚恩
I'm not sure you understand, Sean.
-我不明白什麼  -來了
-What don't I understand? -Here you go, guys.
-謝謝  提米  -謝謝你
-Thanks, Tim. -Yeah, thank you.
這樣手指不會擰擰的
Just so you don't get sticky fingers.
提米  你要幫我們嗎
Tim, can you help us?
我們要賭一賭輸贏
We're trying to settle a bet.
哦
Uh-oh.
聽過約拿斯索克嗎
Ever heard of Jonas Salk?
當然  被治癒的小兒麻痹症患者
Sure. Cured polio.
-聽過愛因斯坦嗎  -嘿
-Ever heard of Albert Einstein? -Hey.
傑洛藍勃呢  聽過嗎
How about Gerald Lambeau? Ever heard of him?
-沒有  -謝謝
-No. -Thank you, Tim.
-誰賭贏了  -我贏了
-So who won the bet? -I did.
這不是我的事
This isn't about me, Sean.
我跟這年輕人比起來不算什麼
I'm nothing compared to this young man.
你聽過傑洛藍勃嗎
You ever hear of Gerald Lambeau?
在1905年
In 1905 there were hundreds
有許多以研究宇宙聞名的教授
of professors renown for their study of the universe.
但改變世界的卻是個
But it was a 26-year-old Swiss patent clerk,
趁閒暇時研究物理的26歲辦事員
doing physics in his spare time, who changed the world.
你可以想像如果愛因斯坦...
Can you imagine if Einstein would have given that up...
每天都喝得爛醉的話會怎樣
just to get drunk with his buddies in Vienna every night.
我們都會失去一些東西
We all would have lost something.
而提米絕不會聽過他
Tim would never have heard of him.
-非常戲劇化  -不是
-Pretty dramatic, Gerry. -No, it isn't, Sean.
這孩子有天賦
This boy has that gift.
他只是沒方向  我們應該給他
He just doesn't got the direction, but we can give that to him.
傑洛  在60年代
Hey, Gerry, in the 1960s,
曾有一個密西根大學畢業的年輕人
there was a young man graduated from University of Michigan.
他的數學很出色
Did some brilliant work in mathematics.
特別是有界集函數
Specifically, bounded harmonic functions.
他到柏克萊當助教  潛力驚人
Then he went on to Berkeley. He was assistant professor. Showed amazing potential.
然後在蒙大拿州贏得競賽
Then he moved to Montana, and he blew the competition away.
-好  他是誰  -泰德卡辛斯基
-Yeah, so who was he? -Ted Kaczynski.
沒聽過
Haven't heard of him.
-提米  -喲
-Hey, Timmy! -Yo!
-誰是泰德卡辛斯基  -郵包炸彈狂
-Who's Ted Kaczynski? -Unabomber.
那就是我要說的
That's exactly what I'm talking about.
-他需要我們指點方向  -嗯...
-We gotta give this kid direction. -Yeah...
他能貢獻世人  我們能幫他做到
He can contribute to the world, and we can help him do that.
方向是一回事  操縱是另一回事
Direction's one thing. Manipulation's another.
-尚恩...-你要讓他自己發掘...
-Sean... -We have to let him find...
尚恩  我不是
I'm not sitting at home every night
每晚坐在家裡絞盡腦汁...
twisting my mustache and hatching a plan...
策劃怎麼摧毀他的人生
to ruin this boy's life!
我18歲就會做高級數學
I was doing advanced mathematics when I was 18,
然而之後仍舊花了20年才得到菲爾茲獎
and it still took me over 20 years to do something worthy of a Field's medal.
也許他不想照你的想法去做
Maybe he doesn't want what you want.
人生不只是一個他媽的獎章
There's more to life than a fucking Field's medal.
這太重要了  而且這要超越個人立場
This is too important, Sean, and it's above personal rivalry.
等等  我們談的是這孩子
Wait a minute. Let's talk about the boy.
為何不給他時間想清楚要什麼
Why don't we give him time to figure out what he wants?
很棒的理論  可以為你創造奇跡  是嗎
That's a wonderful theory, Sean. It worked wonders for you, didn't it?
對  你這個自負的混蛋
Yeah, it did, you arrogant fucking prick!
我很遺憾  很遺憾今天我來了
Oh, I'm sorry. I'm sorry that I came here today.
我是來這是出於好意  我想讓你參與這件事
I came here out of courtesy. I wanted to keep you in the loop.
我很高興能夠參與
Nice to be in the loop.
那孩子此刻正在我安排的面談中
The boy's in a meeting right now I set up for him over at McNeil.
威爾  我不清楚你的意思
Well, Will, I'm not exactly sure what you mean.
我們已經給你職位了
We've already offered you a position.
這年頭做事沒人不拿酬金的
Nobody in this town works without a retainer, guys.
你們認為找得到  我祝福你們
You think you can find somebody who does, you have my blessing.
但沒有人可以像我做得那麼好
But I think we all know that person is not gonna represent you as well as I can.
我們已給你年薪八萬四加福利
Will, our offer is $84,000 a year.
酬金  酬金
Retainer! Retainer.
你是要我們現在給你現金
You want us to give you cash right now?
慢點...我沒那麼說
Whoa-ho-ho. Easy... Now, I didn't say that.
這麼說來  這種情況下  對你來說
Allegedly, your situation, for you,
如果我口袋裡有兩百塊...
would be concurrently improved if I had...
你們的處境會同時獲得改善
$200 in my back pocket right now.
我不認為我能...賴瑞
I don't think I can... Larry?
-我有73塊  -你收支票嗎
-I've got $73. -Will you take a check?
我說你們這種舉止相當可疑
Let me tell you something. You're suspect.
對  你們  我不知道你們的聲譽怎樣
Yeah, you. I don't know what your reputation is in this town,
但耍這種花招
but after the shit you tried to pull today,
我一定會調查
you can bet I'll be looking into you.
關於我們未來的合作
Now, any business we have heretofore,
請和我的律師談
you can speak with my aforementioned attorney.
再見  先生們
Good day, gentlemen.
在那天到來前  拼命幹活吧
And until that day comes, keep your ear to the grindstone.
-怎麼樣  -很好
-How's it going? -Fine.
嗯
Yeah.
好的
Good.
-要幫忙嗎  -不要
-Want some help? -No!
給我看一下  我們要去練球場
Come on. Give me one little peek, and we'll go to the batting cages.
不
No.
我一定要念這個  真的很重要
It is actually important that I learn this.
-對我而言...真的很重要  懂嗎  -好吧
-It's really important... to me, okay? -All right.
-那就在這邊待一整天  -有何不可
-Why don't we just hang out here all day? -Yes, why don't we?
好  多管閒事先生
All right, Mr. Nosey Parker.
既然你打算煩我
Seeing as you're intent on breaking my balls,
-讓我問你一個問題  -好的
-let me ask you a question. -All right.
你有影像記憶力嗎
Do you have a photographic memory?
不知道  我就是記得
I don't know. I just kind of remember.
就好比你可以記得你的電話號碼
I mean, how do you remember your phone number?
就是那麼簡單
You just do.
-你念過有機化學嗎  -一點點
-Have you studied organic chemistry? -A little bit.
-為了好玩  -對  為了找樂趣
-Oh, just for fun? -Yeah, for kicks.
念有機化學會有趣
Yeah, it's so much fun studying organic chemistry.
你瘋啦
Are you mad?
你精神失常嗎
Have you completely lost your mind?
沒人會為了好玩念化學
Nobody studies it for fun.
沒有必要  尤其對你這種人而言
It's not a necessity, especially for someone like you.
-我這種人  -對
-Someone like me? -Yeah.
相對公平地把時間分配給練球場和酒吧的人
Someone who divides their time, fairly evenly, between batting cages and bars.
-我說那沒必要  -噢
-I would hardly say it was a necessity. -Oh.
你知道  哈佛有很聰明的人
You know, there are very smart people here at Harvard.
即便是他們也都得花大力氣  因為太難了
Even they have to study, because this is really hard.
然而...你卻如此簡單地做到了  我不懂
And yet... you do it so easily. I don't understand.
我不懂你的大腦怎麼運作
I don't understand how your mind works.
-你彈鋼琴嗎  -別轉移話題
-Did you play the piano? -I want to talk about this.
我在跟你解釋嘛  你會彈嗎
No, I'm trying to explain it to you. Do you play the piano?
-一點點  -當你看著鋼琴  就看到莫劄特
-Yeah, a bit. -So when you look at a piano, you see Mozart.
-我看到筷子  -好  貝多芬  好嗎
-I see "Chopsticks." -All right, well, Beethoven, okay?
他一看到鋼琴  很自然地就會彈
He looked at a piano, and it just made sense to him. He could just play.
-你在說什麼  你是說你會彈琴  -根本不會
-So what are you saying? You play the piano? -Not a lick.
望著鋼琴  我只看到琴鍵  踏板和木頭
I look at a piano, I see a bunch of keys, three pedals and a box of wood.
但貝多芬  莫札特...
But Beethoven, Mozart...
他們看到鋼琴  自然而然就會彈
They saw it. They could just play.
我不會畫畫  連球都打不好
I couldn't paint you a picture. I probably can't hit the ball out of Fenway.
我也不會彈琴
And I can't play the piano.
但你會一小時內做好化學作業
But you can do my O-chem paper in under an hour.
對  我就是有那種才能
Right. Well, I mean, when it came to stuff like that,
就是那麼得心應手
I could always just play.
我只能解釋到這樣
That's the best I can explain it.
-來  我有話告訴你  -嗯
-Come here. I have to tell you something. -Huh?
-我跟你講一件事  -噢
-I have to tell you something. -Oh.
那沒...
Well...
-這不公平  -什麼不公平  什麼
-It's not fair. -What's not fair? What?
我在這邊四年了
I've been here for four years,
直到現在才發現你
and I've only just found you.
起碼你還是發現我啦
Well, you found me.
-你醒著嗎  -沒有
-Are you awake? -No.
你沒睡
Yes, you are.
跟我一起去加州
Come to California with me.
什麼
What?
我要你跟我去加州
I want you to come to California with me.
-你確定嗎  -確定
-You sure about that? -Oh, yeah.
你怎麼知道
Yeah, but how do you know?
不曉得  我就是知道
I don't know. I just know.
但你怎麼會知道
Yeah, but how do you know?
我知道  因為我感覺得到
I know because I feel it.
-因為你說的是很嚴肅的事  -我知道
-Because that's a really serious thing you're saying. -I know.
下禮拜到了加州...
You could be in California next week...
你可能會發現不喜歡我的地方
and you might find out something about me you don't like.
你會希望你沒說過這些話
Maybe you wish you hadn't said that,
但這是無法收回的事
but you know it's such a serious thing you can't take it back.
於是我跟不愛我的人困在加州
Now I'm stuck in California with someone that doesn't really want to be with me,
-她卻希望一切能收回  -什麼  什麼是收回
-just wish they had a take-back. -A what? What's a take-back?
我不想收回  我只要你跟我去加州
I don't want a take-back. I just want you to come to California with me.
我不能和你去加州...
Well, I can't go to California with you, so...
為什麼
Why not?
一是因為我在這邊有工作
Well, one, because I got a job here.
二是因為我住這邊
And, two, because I live here.
聽著  你不愛我就該告訴我
Look, um, if you don't love me, you should just tell me.
我沒說不愛你
I'm not saying I don't love you.
那為什麼  那為什麼不去  你怕什麼
Then why? Why won't you come? What are you so scared of?
我怕什麼
What am I so scared of?
你不怕什麼
Well, what aren't you scared of?
你活在沒人挑戰的世界裡...
You live in this safe little world where no one challenges you...
別隨意指摘我的世界怎麼樣
Don't tell me about my world.
你只是想跟低下階層搞一下
You just want to have your little fling with the guy from the other side of town.
然後到斯坦福  你會嫁給你父母認同的...
Then you're gonna go off to Stanford. You're gonna marry some rich prick...
那些有錢的混蛋...
who your parents will approve of...
跟其他富家女坐在一起...
and just sit around with the other trust fund babies...
說你到過貧民窟
and talk about how you went slumming, too, once.
你在說什麼  你為何這麼在乎錢
Why are you saying this? What is your obsession with this money?
我十三歲喪父  繼承家產
My father died when I was 13, and I inherited this money.
我每天醒來  都希望能把錢都還給他
You don't think every day I wake up, and I wish I could give it back.
只要能讓我多陪他一天
That I would give it back in a second if it meant
我會毫不猶豫放棄所有財產
I could have one more day with him.
但我不能  那是我的人生  我面對它
But I can't, and that's my life, and I deal with it.
別把你的害怕推到我身上
So don't put your shit on me when you're the one that's afraid.
我怕  我怕什麼  我他媽的怕什麼
I'm afraid? What am I afraid of? What the fuck am I afraid of?
你怕我  怕我不愛你
You're afraid of me. You're afraid that I won't love you back.
你知道嗎  我也怕
You know what? I'm afraid too.
但我想試試看  起碼我誠實
But fuck it, I want to give it a shot. At least I'm honest with you.
難道我對你不誠實
I'm not honest with you?
不  你的十二個哥哥呢
No, what about your 12 brothers?
好的
All right.
你不能走  不准離開
No, you're not going. You're not leaving.
你想知道什麼  我沒有12個哥哥
What do you want to know? That I don't have 12 brothers?
我他媽的是個孤兒
That I'm a fucking orphan?
-你不會想聽的  -我並不曉得
-You don't want to hear that. -I didn't know that.
你不會想聽我童年被人用香煙燒
You don't want to hear I got fucking cigarettes put out on me when I was little.
-我不曉得  -那不是手術
-I didn't know that. -That this isn't fucking surgery.
那混蛋刺傷我  你不會想聽這種事  史凱蘭
The motherfucker stabbed me. You don't want to hear that shit, Skylar!
-我想要聽  -別跟我說你想聽
-I do want to hear that. -Don't tell me you want that shit!
-因為我想幫你  -幫我  什麼鬼東西
-I want to help you. -Help me? What the fuck?
我臉上有寫著"請救我"嗎
What do I got, a fucking sign on my back that says, "Save me"?
-沒有  -我像要人救的樣子嗎
-No. -Do I look like I need that?
-我想跟你在一起...-別耍我
-No, I just want to be with you... -Don't bullshit me!
-我愛你  -別耍我  別他媽的耍我
-I love you. -Don't bullshit me! Don't you fucking bullshit me!
我愛你
I love you.
我要聽你說你不愛我
I want to hear you say that you don't love me.
因為如果你說出口...
Because if you say that...
那麼我就不再打電話給你...
then I won't call you...
不再出現在你的生命裡
and I won't be in your life.
我不愛你
I don't love you.
很多人都無從得知自己的天賦
Most people never get to see how brilliant they can be.
因為找不到相信他們的老師
They don't find teachers that believe in them.
於是他們深信自己很笨
They get convinced they're stupid.
希望你能感激他所做的
I hope you appreciate what he's doing,
因為我知道他很喜歡跟你合作
because I've seen how much he enjoys working with you,
我沒有反對你
not against you.
你好  威爾
Hello, Will.
湯姆  拿點咖啡來
Tom, can you get us some coffee?
好的
Sure.
好的  我看看
Now, let's see.
很好  正確
Good. This is correct.
你用了麥克老林公式
I see you used Maclaurin here.
我不知道那玩意叫什麼  但是...
Yeah, I don't know what you call it, but...
這樣不對
This can't be right.
這會很難堪
This would be very embarrassing.
-你是否想過...-我確信是對的
-Did you ever consider... -I'm pretty sure it's right.
聽著  我們以後能在尚恩的辦公室做心理治療嗎
Hey, look, can we do this at Sean's office from now on?
我得放下工作過來  坐車很煩
Because I got to knock off work to come here and the commute is killing me.
-好  可不可能...-那是對的
-Yeah, sure. Did you think of the possibility... -That's right.
那是對的  把它帶回家吧
It's right. Just take it home with you.
麥尼爾的面談怎麼了
What happened at the McNeil meeting?
我去不了  我有約會
I couldn't go. I had a date.
所以我派我的談判代表去
So I sent my chief negotiator.
你自己的時間愛幹嘛隨你
On your own time, you can do whatever you like, Will.
但我安排的會談
But when I set up a meeting with my associates,
你沒出現  就會讓我丟臉
and you don't show up, it reflects poorly on me.
-好  那就別安排了  -我不會
-Then don't set up any more meetings. -I won't.
我會通通取消
I'll cancel them.
我會親自給你工作  讓你看看外面的世界
I'll give you a job myself. I just wanted you to see what was out there.
或許我不想一輩子做解說員
Maybe I don't want to spend the rest of my fucking life explaining shit to people.
但你可以表示感激吧
I think you could show me some appreciation.
感激  你知道這有多容易嗎
A little appreciation? Do you know how easy this is for me?
你知道這他媽的有多容易嗎  別他媽的說笑了
Do you have any fucking idea how easy this is? This is a fucking joke.
我很遺憾你不會解...真的...
I'm sorry you can't do this... I really am...
因為我不想坐在這兒看你摸索
Because I wouldn't have to fucking sit here
然後搞砸掉
and watch you fumble around and fuck it up.
這樣你就會有更多的時間花天酒地  是嗎
Then you'd have more time to sit around and get drunk instead, wouldn't you?
沒錯  這完全浪費我的時間
You're right. This is probably a total waste of my time.
你說得對
You're right, Will.
我解不出來  但你會做到
I can't do this proof, but you can.
說到這個
And when it comes to that,
這個世界只有少數人...
it's only about just a handful of people in the world...
才能看出你我的差別
who can tell the difference between you and me.
-我是其中之一  -我很遺憾
-But I'm one of them. -Sorry.
我也是
Yeah, so am l.
我常希望沒遇到你
Most days I wish I never met you,
這樣我夜裡就能睡得著
because then I could sleep at night.
不用惦記在外面
I didn't have to walk around with the knowledge
有個像你這樣的人
that there was someone like you out there.
我就不必看著你糟蹋天賦
I didn't have to watch you throw it all away.
比爾  等等  聽到沒
Bill, hold it. Did you hear that?
摩根
Morgan!
如果你還敢在我媽房裡看A片
If you're watching pornos in my mom's room again,
我就揍扁你
I'm gonna give you a fucking beating!
怎麼了  老兄
What's up, fellas?
摩根  要打手槍在你家裡打  髒死了
Morgan, why don't you jerk off in your own fucking house. That's fucking filthy.
我家沒錄影機
I don't have a V.C.R. in my house.
他媽的我不管
Come on. Not in my glove.
我沒用手套
I didn't use the glove.
那是我的小聯盟手套
That's my Little League glove.
你要我怎麼做
What do you want me to do?
你怎麼搞的
I mean, what's wrong with you?
操棒球手套啊
You'll hump a baseball glove?
我沒有  我用它清乾淨
I-I just used it for cleanup.
別在我媽房裡打手槍了
Stop jerking off in my mother's room.
-這屋裡還有別台錄影機嗎  -真可悲
-Is there another V.C.R. in the house? -It's just sad, bro.
我為什麼該為國安局做事
So why do you think I should work for the National Security Agency?
你將研究尖端科技
Well, you'd be working on the cutting edge.
接觸別處看不到的科技
You'd be exposed to the kind of technology you wouldn't see anywhere else,
因為這些都已被列為機密
because we've classified it.
超弦理論  混沌數學  高級演算法
Superstring theory, chaos math, advanced algorithms.
破解密碼
Code breaking.
那是其中一個層面
That's one aspect of what we do.
得了  那就是你們做的事
Oh, come on. That is what you do.
你們處理八成的情報量
You guys handle 80 of the intelligence workload.
是中情局的七倍大
You're seven times the size of the C.I.A.
我們不喜歡自誇  但你說對了
We don't like to brag about that, Will, but you're exactly right.
我的看法  問題不是
So the way I see it, the question isn't:
"你幹嘛為國安局做事"
"Why should you work for the N.S.A.?"
而是  "你為何不做"
The question is: "Why shouldn't you?"
我為何不為國安局做事
Why shouldn't I work for the N.S.A.?
很難的問題  讓我想想
That's a tough one, but I'll take a shot.
若我為國安局做事  國安局的人給我個密碼破解
Say I'm working at the N.S.A. and somebody puts a code on my desk.
其他人都束手無策的密碼
Something no one else can break.
或許我試了  也破解了
Maybe I take a shot at it and maybe I break it.
我很滿意  因為表現良好
I'm real happy with myself because I did my job well.
但也許那個密碼
But maybe that code was the location
是位於北非或中東的叛軍位置
of some rebel army in North Africa or Middle East.
他們發現後轟炸叛軍藏身地
Once they have that location, they bomb the village where the rebels are hiding.
陌生的
Fifteen hundred people that I never met,
毫無瓜葛的一千五百人因此喪命
never had no problem with, get killed.
然後政客高呼"派遣海軍陸戰隊維護當地秩序"
Now the politicians are saying, "Send in the Marines to secure the area,"
他們才不在乎
because they don't give a shit.
被射殺的不會是他們的子女
It won't be their kid over there getting shot,
他們也算參了軍
just like it wasn't them when their number got called
因為他們都加入了後備部隊
because they were in the National Guard.
而在那邊中彈的南區孩子
It'll be some kid from Southie over there taking shrapnel in the ass.
回國後發現他以前工作的工廠...
He comes back to find the plant he used to work at...
被移轉到他去打仗的國家
got exported to the country he got back from,
害他中彈的敵人搶了他的飯碗...
and the guy who put the shrapnel in his ass got his old job...
因為那個人一天工資不到一元
because he'll work for 15 cents a day and no bathroom breaks.
最後他發現他會上戰場...
Meanwhile, he realizes the only reason he was over there in the first place...
是為了得到該國的廉價原油
was so we could install a government that would sell us oil at a good price.
好讓石油公司
Of course, the oil companies used
利用戰爭恐慌抬高國內油價
a skirmish over there to scare up domestic oil prices.
小賺一番
A cute little ancillary benefit for them,
但兩塊五一加侖有個屁用
but it are'nt helping my buddy at 2.50 a gallon.
他們得花時間把石油運回國
They're taking their sweet time bringing the oil, of course.
或許還請了一個酗酒船長
Maybe they even took the liberty to hire an alcoholic skipper,
他愛喝馬丁尼  玩冰山滑雪
who likes to drink martinis and fucking play slalom with the icebergs.
不久他撞上冰山  原油外漏...
It are'nt too long till he hits one, spills the oil...
殺光北大西洋的海洋生物
and kills all the sea life in the North Atlantic.
現在我朋友失業  也開不起車
So now my buddy's out of work, he can't afford to drive,
他走路去面試...
so he's walking to the fucking job interviews...
這很難受  因為炮彈片讓你慢性出血
which sucks because the shrapnel in his ass is giving him chronic hemorrhoids.
與此同時  他饑寒交迫  因為每次想吃東西
Meanwhile, he's starving, because every time he tries to get a bite to eat,
唯一的特餐就是...
the only blue plate special they're serving...
北大西洋鱈魚
is North Atlantic scrod with Quaker State.
那麼我會怎麼想  我有更好的點子
So what did I think? I'm holding out for something better.
幹  我乾脆射殺我朋友算了
I figure, fuck it. While I'm at it, why not just shoot my buddy,
把他的工作留給敵人
take his job, give it to his sworn enemy,
提高油價  轟炸村莊  打死小海豹
hike up gas prices, bomb a village, club a baby seal,
吸食大麻  加入後備部隊
hit the hash pipe and join the National Guard?
我還可因此被選為總統
I can be elected president.
-你感覺孤單嗎  -什麼
-You feel like you're alone? -What?
你有心靈伴侶嗎
Do you have a soul mate?
我有...說清楚點
Do I have a... Define that.
能夠和你匹敵的人
Somebody who challenges you.
我有查克
Uh, Chuckie.
不  查克是你的家人
No, Chuckie's family.
現在還因為你車禍受傷躺在醫院
He'd lie down in fucking traffic for you.
我指的是敞開你心扉  觸動你心靈的人
I'm talking about someone who opens up things for you, touches your soul.
-我有...我有...-誰
-I got... I got... -Who?
-有很多  -說出來
-I got plenty. -Well, name them.
莎士比亞  尼采  佛斯特
Shakespeare, Nietzsche, Frost,
奧康納  康得  洛克...
O'Connor, Kant, Pope, Locke...
很棒  他們都死了
That's great. They're all dead.
-對我而言  他們沒死  -你無法和他們對談
-Not to me they're not. -You don't have a lot of dialogue with them.
你不能回應他們
You can't give back to them, Will.
除非你有仙丹
Not without some serious smelling salts and a heater.
對  那就是我所說的
That's what I'm saying.
如果你不踏出第一步...
You'll never have that kind of relationship in a world...
你絕不會有那種關係
where you're always afraid to take the first step,
因為你只看到負面的事
because all you see is every negative thing ten miles down the road.
-你要擺出教授架子了  -少跟我來這套
-You gonna take the professor's side on this? -Don't give me a line of shit.
-沒有  -我不想做那個工作
-No. -I didn't want the job.
不關工作的事  我不管你是否為政府工作
It's not about the job. I don't care if you work for the government.
但你能隨心所欲  不受束縛
But you can do anything you want. You are bound by nothing.
你熱愛什麼  想要什麼
What are you passionate about? What do you want?
有人一輩子砌磚...
There are guys who work their entire life laying brick...
讓孩子擁有像你現在的機會
so their kids have a chance at the opportunities you have here.
-我可沒要求這機會  -不
-I didn't ask for this. -No.
不  你與生俱來就有
You were born with it,
別逃避說  "我可沒要求"
so don't cop out behind: "I didn't ask for this."
-什麼叫逃避  砌磚哪裡不對  -沒有
-What do you mean, cop out? What's wrong with laying brick? -Nothing.
我為別人家蓋房子  有什麼不對
There's nothing wrong. That's somebody's home I'm building.
對  我爸砌磚  好嗎
Right. My dad laid brick, okay?
他拼命幹活讓我受教育
Busted his ass so I could have an education.
沒錯  那是可敬的行業
Exactly. That's an honorable profession.
修車哪不對
What's wrong with fixing somebody's car?
因為我的工作  別人得以上班  這是很光榮的事
Someone will get to work the next day because of me. That's honor in that.
是的  是很光榮
Yeah, there is, Will. There is honor in that.
搭40分鐘火車...
There's honor in taking that 40-minute train ride...
讓大學生上課有乾淨的環境也很可敬
so those college kids could come in in the morning and their floors are clean.
-他們的垃圾箱空了  這才叫真正的工作  -對
-And their wastebaskets are empty. That's real work. -That's right.
對  是很可敬  相信你選擇這份工作
And that's honorable. I'm sure that's why you took that job.
正是為了這份榮耀
I mean, for the honor of it.
我只是有個小問題  你到哪裡都能做工友
I just have a little question here. You could be a janitor anywhere.
為何挑中
Why did you work
全世界一流的科技學府
at the most prestigious technical college in the whole fucking world?
夜裡偷偷地解算...
Why did you sneak around at night and finish other people's formulas...
世上只有兩個人會的方程式
that only one or two people in the world could do and then lie about it?
我看不到其中的榮耀
because I don't se a lot of honor in that, Will.
你真正想做什麼
So what do you really wanna do?
我想當牧羊人
I wanna be a shepherd.
真的
Really?
我想搬到納旭
I wanna move up to Nashua, get a nice little spread,
買塊地皮放羊
get some sheep and tend to them.
-也許你該那麼做  -什麼
-Maybe you should go do that. -What?
要自慰的話
You know, if you're gonna jerk off,
何不回家弄條濕毛巾搞
why don't you just do it at home with a moist towel?
-你在趕我  -對  他媽的滾出去
-You're chucking me? -Yeah, get the fuck outta here.
-不  不  不  時間還沒到  -時間到了
-No, no, no, time's not up yet. -Yeah, it is.
我不走  不
I'm not leaving. No.
你在逃避我的問題  你在浪費我的時間
You're not gonna answer, you're wasting my time.
我以為我們是朋友
I thought we were friends.
-遊戲時間結束了  懂不  -你為什麼趕我走
-Playtime's over, okay? -Why are you kicking me out?
你想教我人生大道理  看看你  糟老頭
You're lecturing me on life? Look at you, you fucking burnout.
-是什麼讓你過下去  -跟你合作
-What winds your clock? -Working with you.
你的心靈伴侶在哪
Where's your soul mate?
你要談心靈伴侶嗎  她在哪
You wanna talk about soul mates? Where is she?
-死了  -對  她他媽的已經死了
-Dead. -That's right. She's fucking dead.
你就不敢再為人生下賭注了
She fucking dies and you just cash in your chips and you walk away?
起碼我玩過一把
At least I played a hand.
那你輸了  輸得很慘
You played a hand and you lost. You lost a big fucking hand.
有些人即便輸得那麼慘還是會再下注
Some people will lose a big hand like that and have the sack to ante up again.
看著我  你想要什麼
Look at me. What do you wanna do?
你和你那些屁話  對每個人你都有狗屁答案
You and your bullshit. You got a bullshit answer for everybody.
卻答不出來我提出的那麼簡單的問題
But I ask you a very simple question and you can't give me a straight answer,
因為你不知道
because you don't know.
再見  躲貓貓
I'll see ya, Bo-peep.
-去你的  -你是牧羊人
-Fuck you. -You're the shepherd.
牧羊人
Shepherd.
混蛋
White little prick.
我只是想  你知道的
I just wanted to, you know, um,
趁你還沒走打電話給你...
call you up, uh, before you left, um...
我正在面試談工作
I've been taking all these jobs interviews and stuff,
我不會只當營造工人
so I'm not gonna be just a construction worker.
你知道我並不在乎
Well, you know, I never really cared about that.
是的
Yeah.
我愛你
I love you.
威爾
Will?
你保重
You take care.
再見
Bye.
威爾
Will
威爾  好了  做完了
Will, that's it! We're done!
我在你辦公室  那孩子沒來
I'm sitting in your office and the boy isn't here.
都五點十分了
Well, it's ten past 5:00.
遲到一小時十分
An hour and ten minutes late.
他如果沒出現  我會向法院如實提出報告
Well, if he doesn't show up and I file a report saying he wasn't here...
他去坐牢  我不會愧疚的
and he goes back to jail, he won't be on my conscience.
好  很好
Okay. Fine.
怎麼了
What's up?
謝謝
Thanks.
啊  真爽
Ah! God, that's good.
你馬子怎麼樣
So how's your lady?
她走了
Ah, she's gone.
走了  到哪裡去了
Gone? Gone where?
醫學院  加州的醫學院
Med school. Medical school in California.
-真的  -嗯
-Really? -Yeah.
-幾時的事  -一禮拜前
-When was this? -It was, like, a week ago.
好爛
That sucks.
那些會談幾時搞完
So, uh, when are you done with those meetings?
大概是我過了21歲之後的那個星期
I think the week after I'm 21.
他們要給你工作嗎
They gonna hook ya up with a job or what?
對  他媽的往後50年要呆坐在房間裡做無聊的算術
Yeah, fucking sit in a room and do long division for the next 50 years.
可能會攢不少錢
Nah, probably make some nice bank though.
我會成為他媽的實驗室老鼠
I'm gonna be a fucking lab rat.
好過這鬼東西  離開這裡
Better than this shit. Way outta here.
幹嘛要走
What do I want a way outta here for?
我他媽的下輩子都要住這兒
I mean, I'm gonna fucking live here the rest of my life.
我們會成為鄰居  會當爸爸
You know, be neighbors. You know, have little kids.
一起帶孩子們去球場打小聯盟
Fucking take them to Little League together up Foley Field.
你是我的死黨  所以別誤會
Look, you're my best friend, so don't take this the wrong way.
但20年後你如果還住在這兒
But in 20 years if you're still living here,
到我家看球賽
coming over to my house to watch the Patriots games,
還在蓋房子  我他媽的會殺了你
still working construction, I'll fucking kill ya.
那不是恐嚇  我認真的  我會宰了你
That's not a threat. That's a fact. I'll fucking kill ya.
你在胡扯什麼
What the fuck are you talking about?
-你擁有我們沒有的天賦  -拜託
-Look, you got something none of us have. -Oh, come on!
為何大家都這麼說  難道是我對不起自己嗎
Why is it always this? I fucking owe it to myself to do this or that.
我就是不想那麼做  那又怎麼辦
What if I don't want to?
不  不  不  去你的  你沒有對不起自己
No, no, no. Fuck you. You don't owe it to yourself.
你對不起我
You owe it to me,
因為我明天醒來五十歲了
because tomorrow I'm gonna wake up and I'll be 50,
還在幹這種事
and I'll still be doing this shit.
無所謂
That's all right. That's fine.
而你已擁有百萬獎券
I mean, you're sitting on a winning lottery ticket.
卻窩囊的不敢兌現  狗屁
You're too much of a pussy to cash it in, and that's bullshit.
因為我會不惜一切交換你所擁有的
because I'd do fucking anything to have what you got.
其他人也是
So would any of these fucking guys.
你再待20年是侮辱我們
Be an insult to us if you're still here in 20 years.
窩在這裡是浪費你時間
Hanging around here is a fucking waste of your time.
-你懂什麼  -我不懂
-You don't know that. -I don't?
你不懂
No. You don't know that.
我不懂  我告訴你我懂什麼
Oh, I don't know that. Let me tell you what I do know.
我每天到你家接你
Every day I come by your house, and I pick you up.
我們出去喝酒笑鬧  那很棒
We go out and have a few drinks and few laughs, and it's great.
但你知道我一天中最棒的時刻是什麼
You know what the best part of my day is?
只有十秒
It's for about ten seconds:
從停車到走到你家門口這段時間
from when I pull up to the curb and when I get to your door.
因為每次我敲門
because I think maybe I'll get up there
都希望你不在家
and I'll knock on the door and you won't be there.
不說"再見"  或是"明天見"
No "good-bye," no "see ya later."
什麼都沒有  你就是走了
No nothing. You just left.
我懂得不多  但我很清楚
I don't know much, but I know that.
真是亂來  尚恩
This is a disaster, Sean.
我讓你參與  是要你幫這孩子
I brought you in here because I wanted you to help me with the boy,
-不是趕走他  -我知道怎麼應付這孩子
-not to run him out. -I know what I'm doing with the boy.
我不管你跟他有什麼默契
I don't care if you have a rapport with the boy!
我不在乎你們花我的錢開心
I don't care if you have a few laughs, even at my expense.
-但你敢破壞我的事看看  -破壞
-But don't you dare undermine what I'm trying to do here. -Undermine?
這孩子目前很脆弱
This boy is at a fragile point right now.
我瞭解他很脆弱  他還有些問題
I do understand. He is at a fragile point. He's got problems.
他有什麼問題  當工友或坐牢會比較好嗎
What problems does he have? That he's better off as a janitor, in jail?
跟一群智障在一起會比較好嗎
Better hanging out with a bunch of retarded gorillas?
你想他為什麼那麼做  你曉得為什麼嗎
Why do you think he does that? You have any fucking clue why?
他能應付問題  應付工作
He can handle the problems. He can handle the work.
顯然也應付得了你
He obviously handled you.
聽我說  他為何躲避
Listen to me. Why is he hiding?
為何不信任人
Why doesn't he trust anybody?
因為他生下來遇到的頭一遭事
Because the first thing that happened to him,
就是他被本應該最愛他的人遺棄
he was abandoned by the people who were supposed to love him the most.
別跟我講佛洛伊德的屁話
Don't give me that Freudian crap.
他為什麼跟你所謂的智障混
Why does he hang out with those retarded gorillas, as you call them?
因為如果他叫他們扁你  他們會照辦
Because any one of them, if he asked them to, would take a bat to your head.
-那叫做義氣  -是喔  很感人
-That's called loyalty. -Yeah, that's very touching.
他應付誰了
Who's he handling?
他在別人先離開他之前就把別人趕走
He pushes people away before they have a chance to leave him.
那是防衛心理  好嗎
It's a defense mechanism, all right?
他因此孤獨了20年
For 20 years, he's been alone because of that.
你現在逼他  事情會重演
If you push him right now, it's gonna be the same thing all over again.
我不會讓他重蹈覆轍
I'm not gonna let that happen to him.
-別那麼做  -什麼
-Don't you do that. -What?
別讓他認為放棄沒關係
Don't infect him with the idea that it's okay to quit,
或者失敗也沒關係
that it's okay to be a failure.
因為絕對有關係  尚恩
Because it's not okay, Sean!
如果你是氣我成功
And if you're angry at me for being successful,
或是氣我...
for being what you could have been...
-我沒氣你  -不  你有氣我
-I'm not angry at you. -Oh, yes, you're angry at me.
憎惡我  但我不會因為比你成功而向你賠不是
You resent me, but I'm not gonna apologize for any success I've had.
你氣我做到你本來能做到的事
You're angry at me for doing what you could have done!
你捫心自問  尚恩...捫心自問...
But ask yourself, Sean... Ask yourself...
你要威爾也有那種感受
if you want Will to feel that way...
你要他感覺像失敗者
if you want him to feel like a failure?
你這個自大狂
You arrogant shit!
我不去同學會的原因
That's why I don't come to the goddamn reunions,
是因為受不了你的眼神
because I can't stand that look in your eye.
-那種屈尊難堪的眼神  -得了  尚恩
-That condescending, embarrassed look. -Oh, come on, Sean.
你認為我失敗  我有自知之明
You think I'm a failure. I know who I am.
我為自己感到驕傲
I'm proud of what I do.
那是自覺的選擇  我沒搞砸
It was a conscious choice. I didn't fuck up!
你和你朋友認為我很可憐
And you and your cronies think I'm some sort of pity case.
你和你那些狗屁課程
You and your kiss-ass chorus following
你老是提自己的菲爾茲獎
you around going, "The Field's medal!"
你怎麼還是這麼怕失敗
Why are you still so fucking afraid of failure?
你是嫉妒我有獎章嗎  天哪
It's about my medal, isn't it? Oh, God,
我回家拿給你  送給你好了
I could go home and get it for you. You can have it.
把獎章他媽的塞進你自己的屁眼裡
Shove the medal up your fucking ass, all right?
因為我不在乎你的獎章
because I don't give a shit about your medal,
因為我在你還沒當上數學之神以前就認識你了
because I knew you before you were a mathematical god,
早在你滿臉青春痘  思鄉
when you were pimple-faced and homesick
不知要尿在床的那一頭的時候
and didn't know what side of the bed to piss on.
是  你過去現在都比我聰明
Yeah, you were smarter than me then and you're smarter than me now.
那麼你的人生變成這樣別怪我
So don't blame me for how your life turned out.
我沒怪你  這跟你無關
I don't blame you! It's not about you!
你這數學混球  是關於那孩子
You mathematical dick! It's about the boy!
他是個好孩子
He's a good kid!
我不會看著你像現在糟蹋我這般糟蹋他
And I won't see you fuck him up like you're trying to fuck up me right now.
我不會看著你讓他也感覺是失敗者
I won't see you make him feel like a failure too!
他不會失敗
He won't be a failure!
但你如果逼迫他  如果驅使他
But if you push him! If you ride him!
我能有今天成就是逼出來的
I am what I am today because I was pushed and because I learned to push myself.
他不是你  你聽懂沒
He's not you! You get that!
我待會再來
I can come back.
不  進來  我正要走
No, come in. Uh, I was just leaving.
這是他和我之間的陳年往事
A lot of that stuff goes back a long way between me and him.
你知道  跟你無關
You know. Not about you.
那是什麼
What is that?
你的檔案  我要送回去給法官評估
This is your file. I have to send it back to the judge for evaluation.
你不會讓我失敗吧
Oh. Hey, you're not gonna fail me, are you?
裡面怎麼寫
What's it say?
-你想看嗎  -為什麼
-Wanna read it? -Why?
你有過那種經驗嗎
Have you had any, uh, experience with that?
20年的輔導  我看過很慘的事
Twenty years of counseling. Yeah, I've seen some pretty awful shit.
你有那方面的經驗嗎
I mean, have you had any experience with that?
-個人的  -是的
-Personally? -Yeah.
我有
Yeah, I have.
我想肯定不好
It sure are'nt good.
我爸是酒鬼
My father was an alcoholic.
爛醉如泥
Mean fucking drunk.
他喝醉回家就想打人
He'd come home hammered, looking to whale on somebody.
我激怒他以保護媽媽和弟弟
So I'd provoke him so he wouldn't go after my mother and little brother.
他若晚上帶工具回來就精彩了
Interesting nights when he wore his rings.
他把扳手
He used to just put a wrench,
棍子和皮帶擺在桌上
a stick and a belt on the table.
-然後說  "選一個"  -我會挑皮帶
-Just say, "Choose." -Well, I gotta go with the belt there.
我通常挑扳手
I used to go with the wrench.
為什麼是扳手
Why the wrench?
因為是"操他的"
because fuck him, that's why.
-你養父  -對
-Your foster father? -Yeah.
這麼說來  是不是威爾有"依附情結"
So, uh, what is it, like, Will has an attachment disorder?
就是這麼回事
Is it all that stuff?
害怕被遺棄
Fear of abandonment?
那是我跟史凱蘭分手的原因嗎
Is that why I broke up with Skylar?
-我不曉得你們分手了  -我提出的分手
-I didn't know you had. -Yeah, I did.
-想談嗎  -不想
-You wanna talk about it? -No.
威爾  我知道的不多
Hey, Will, I don't know a lot.
但你看到這個沒  這些事
You see this? All this shit?
這不是你的錯
It's not your fault.
是的  我知道
Yeah, I know that.
看著我  孩子
Look at me, son.
-這不是你的錯  -我知道
-It's not your fault. -I know.
這不是你的錯
No. It's not your fault.
我知道
I know.
不  不  你不知道  這不是你的錯
No, no, you don't. It's not your fault.
-嗯  -我知道
-Hmm? -I know.
-這不是你的錯  -好的
-It's not your fault. -All right.
這不是你的錯
It's not your fault.
-這不是你的錯  -別整我
-It's not your fault. -Don't fuck with me.
這不是你的錯
It's not your fault.
別整我好嗎  別整我
Don't fuck with me, all right? Don't fuck with me, Sean, not you.
這不是你的錯
It's not your fault.
我的天...
My God...
我的天  真對不起  我的天
My God! I'm so sorry! My God!
去他們的  好嗎
Fuck them, okay?
-有何貴幹  -我是威爾杭汀  我來談工作
-Can I help you? -Yeah, I'm Will Hunting. I'm here about a position.
你能座一下稍等片刻嗎
Could you just have a seat for a moment?
對  大廳裡是有一位杭汀先生
Yes, there's a Mr. Hunting in the lobby.
你選擇哪一個
Which one did you take?
麥尼爾那邊  教授幫我安排的工作之一
I was over at McNeil. It's one of the jobs the professor set me up with.
我還沒告訴他  但我和老闆談過...
I haven't told him yet, but I went down there and talked to my boss...
新老闆人好像不錯
My new boss. He seemed like a good guy.
-那是你要的嗎  -對  我想是吧
-Is that what you want? -Yeah, you know, I think so.
做得好  恭喜
Well, good for you. Congratulations.
謝謝
Thanks.
時間到了
Time's up.
就...就這樣了  我們結束了
So that's... So that's it? So we're done?
對  就這樣
Yeah, that's it.
你結束了  自由了
You're done. You're a free man.
我要你知道  我...
Well, um, I just want you to know, Sean, that...
不客氣
You're welcome, Will.
希望我們保持聯絡
So, you know, I hope we keep in touch, you know.
我也希望
Yeah, me too.
我會旅行一陣子  會有點難  但...
I'll be traveling around a bit. It'll be a little hard, but, uh...
不過我有答錄機  我會查看留言
I've got an answering machine at the college I'll be checking in with.
拿著  我的號碼
So, here's the number.
你打來  我會馬上回電話
You call that. I'll get back to you right away.
你知道  我要再下注...
Yeah, you know, I figured I'm just gonna...
看看這次賭到什麼
put my money back on the table and see what kind of cards I get.
做自己真心想做的事  你就沒事了
You do what's in your heart, son. You'll be fine.
-謝謝你  尚恩  -呃...
-Thank you, Sean. -Uh...
謝謝你  威爾
Thank you, Will.
這違反醫師病人關係嗎
Hey, does this violate the patient-doctor relationship?
除非你抓我屁股
Naw. Only if you grab my ass.
-保重  -你也是
-Take care. -You too.
嗯
Yeah.
嘿
Hey.
祝你好運  孩子
Good luck, son.
兩瓶啤酒
Two beers.
什麼事  你們去了嗎
What's up? Did you guys go?
沒有  我得勸退他
No. I had to talk him down.
-你怎麼不約束他  -摩根有一堆屁話
-Why didn't you yoke him? -Little Morgan's got a lot of scrap to him.
天天有人想扁他
People try to whip his ass every week.
-他還不讓步  -講我什麼壞話
-Fucking kid won't back down. -What are you saying about me?
我跟你講話嗎  幹你屁事
Was I talking to you? None of your fucking business.
-幫我弄瓶啤酒  -我叫了兩瓶
-Go get me a beer. -I ordered two beers!
-渾蛋  -幹嘛  賤貨
-Hey, asshole. -What, bitch?
-生日快樂  -以為我們忘了嗎  賤貨
-Happy birthday. -Thought we forgot, huh, bitch?
-快點  -我去  我去
-Come on! -I'm going. I'm going.
誰先
All right. Who's first?
-混蛋  -誰先
-Come on, motherfucker! -Who's first?
丹尼男孩
Oh, Danny boy
你的禮物
Here's your present.
-快點  兄弟  -什麼
-Come on, bro. -What?
你的新工作要在劍橋來回
Well, we knew you had to get back and forth to Cambridge for your new job.
我不會每天載你  所以...
I knew I wasn't gonna fucking drive you every day, so...
-摩根想給你買免票證  -我沒那麼說
-Morgan wanted to get you a "T" pass. -That's not what I was saying!
但你21歲了
But, uh, you're 21 now.
可以合法喝酒
You're legally allowed to drink,
我們想最好的禮物就是車子
so we figured the best thing for ya was a car.
-喜歡嗎  -這是...
-How do you like it? -This is like...
我這輩子看過最醜的車
It's the ugliest fucking car I've ever seen in my life.
-快  兄弟  -你們怎麼弄的
-Come on, brother. -How'd you guys do this?
我和比爾一起搜括零件
You know, me and Bill scraped together the parts,
摩根每天出去乞討零錢
and Morgan was out panhandling for change every day.
車身都是我搞的
I had the router to do all the bodywork.
我他媽的也出力了
Yeah, I have a fucking job, too, brother.
他煩了我兩年要工作
Guy's been up my ass for two years about a job.
我總得幫他把車的問題解決了
I had to let him help with the car.
你終於有工作了  摩根
So you finally got a job, huh, Morgan?
-有過一個  現在又沒了  -是什麼工作
-Yeah, had one. Now I'm fucked again. -So what is it?
除草工人嗎  什麼工作
A lawn mower? What do ya got?
這他媽的是6缸發動機
It's a straight fucking six.
我和比爾重新打造引擎
Me and Bill rebuilt this engine ourselves here.
這是輛好車  引擎不錯
It's a good car. The engine's good. Engine's good.
-21歲生日快樂  -21歲生日快樂
-Happy 21, Will. -Happy 21, brother.
嗨
Hi.
進來
Come on in.
尚恩  我...
Sean, l, um...
我也是  奇洛
Me too, Gerry.
那就好
Yeah. Good.
聽說你要請假
I heard you're taking some time.
對  我想旅行一陣子  或許寫書
Yeah. Travel a little bit, maybe write.
去哪裡
So where are you going?
印度  中國和巴爾的摩
India and China and Baltimore.
噢
Oh.
你知道幾時回來嗎
You know when you'll be back?
知道  我前兩天收到傳單
Oh. I got this flyer the other day.
上面說半年後72年畢業的那屆要開同學會
It says, uh, class of '72 is having a reunion in six months.
是的  我也收到一張
Yeah, I got one of those too.
你來吧  我請你喝酒
Why don't you come? I'll buy ya a drink.
那種場合的酒是免費的
The drinks at those things are free.
我知道  奇洛  我是在諷刺
I know, Gerry. I was being ironical.
-哦  -現在喝一杯怎麼樣
-Oh. -How about a drink right now?
好主意
Yeah. It's a good idea.
走  這杯我請
Come on. This one's on me.
-我這邊有會中獎的彩券  -噢
-I got the winner right here, pal. -Oh!
對  就是這張
Yes, sir, this is the one.
通往天堂的票
This is my ticket to paradise.
你知道彩券中獎的機率嗎
Do you know what the odds are against winning the lottery?
-多少  四比一  -三千萬比一
-What? Four to one? -About 30 million to one.
但我還是有機會  知道嗎
I still have a shot, you know?
對  跟現在被閃電擊中的
Yes, just about as big chance as you being hit by lightning here
機率一樣
on the staircase right now.
那也有可能  我是說  3200萬
It's a possibility too. I mean, 32 million.
如果你看看...
If you look at the size...
威爾
Will!
Will?
他不在
He's not there.
尚恩  如果教授問起工作的事
Sean, if the professor calls about that job,
跟他說抱歉  我要去找個女孩
just tell him sorry, I had to go see about a girl.
威爾
Will.
小混蛋  偷學我的臺詞
Son of a bitch. He stole my line.